<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Brendan's Blog</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/feed.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Brendan Albano</name>
        
        <email>brendan@brendanalbano.com</email>
        
    </author>
    <updated>2026-02-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>More than telling a story part 2 - Being Clever</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2026-02-27-more-than-telling-a-story-part-2-being-clever.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2026-02-27-more-than-telling-a-story-part-2-being-clever.html</id>
    <published>2026-02-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2026-02-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on February 27, 2026
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>This is part 2 of <strong>More Than Telling a Story</strong>, an open-ended series of posts describing aspects of TTRPGs that resonate with me that aren’t “telling a story.”</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-10-04-more-than-telling-a-story-part-1-describing.html">Part 1: Describing</a></li>
<li>Part 2: Being Clever (this post right here!)</li>
</ul>
<p>This is also maybe the first time in my life I’ve actually written the “part 2” of a series, so that’s exciting!</p>
<h2 id="being-clever">Being Clever</h2>
<h3 id="clever-solutions-to-problems-without-solutions">Clever solutions to problems without solutions</h3>
<p>One of the core elements of OSR style play is when the GM describes an obstacle to the players, and does not have any particular solution in mind, then the players proceed to ask questions about their environment, look at the list of bizarre shit they’ve accumulated in their inventories, and then pitch the GM a solution combining various objects and elements of their ficitonal environment. The GM then becomes an adjudicator of cleverness.</p>
<p>If the GM deems the solution clever enough, it just works! If it’s not quite convincing, or if it involves an element of chance, you might have to make a roll or a saving throw. And of course, if it’s not clever enough, if it doesn’t seem plausible, it just plain might not work.</p>
<p>This back and forth between players and GM when facing the problem with a solution is the play of cleverness.</p>
<h3 id="problems-with-solutions">Problems with solutions</h3>
<p>The problems without solutions style of play is of course an answer to the stumbles that are easy to make when playing TTRPGS with more structured puzzles. But I’ve recently also become curious about this more traditional puzzle solving where you <em>do</em> have solutions. I’m looking forward to running some more escape-room-style puzzle dungeons, and reading <a href="https://puzzledungeon.com/">Direct Sun’s puzzle dungeon posts</a>.</p>
<h3 id="word-wizards">Word Wizards</h3>
<p>In my game <a href="https://ponypress.itch.io/word-wizards">Word Wizards</a>, the central mechanic revolves around knowing a very limited number of words of power, and then bending them to solve any problem your character faces. I remember during a playtest, one character had the word of power “cow” and, faced with a terrifying situation, declared “I’m no COWard” to use their magic to give them bravery. That’s exactly the sort of “being clever” that is the core gameplay of Word Wizards, and is another version of the play of cleverness.</p>
<h3 id="making-your-friends-laugh">Making your friends laugh</h3>
<p>When the player proclaimed “I’m no COWard” I laughed! This might get a whole post of it’s own, but there is another form of cleverness at play in making your friends laugh.</p>
<p>Another example: I was playing a game at a con with a game designer who had been mostly playing larps. We were playing TEETH, which is not a larp, and is a game that leaves room for humor. At one point he made a 4th-wall-breaking joke, which I recall getting a laugh, and I now totally forget what the joke was. But what I remember is that after the game they said that they had forgotten how fun it can be to just make a dumb joke and get a laugh. That’s also the play of cleverness. Just like not every game is about telling stories with your friends, not every game is about telling jokes with your friends, but some games are, and that can be a very satisfying type of play!</p>
<h3 id="parting-thoughts">Parting thoughts</h3>
<p>There is a joy in being clever with or for your fellow players, but there is also a joy in being clever when you are your own audience.</p>
<p>Participating in game jams sometimes also feels like this form of play.</p>
<p>There are lots more ways to enjoy being clever in TTRPGs, and I wanna do the engagement thing where I ask you to share other places you find the joy of being clever in TTRPGs… but I’m still on this “no comments” thing, so go find my email in the about page and email me or something &lt;3.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Endies 2025</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-12-14-the-endies-2025.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-12-14-the-endies-2025.html</id>
    <published>2025-12-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on December 14, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Forget the Ennies, it’s time for the Endies! What RPGs did I play this year? What did I think about them? What intentions am I setting for next year? Let’s play to find out!</p>
<p>Go check out <a href="https://ladytabletop.wordpress.com/2025/11/30/the-endie-awards/">Lady Tabletop’s blog</a> for the origins of the Endies and maybe to find more links to other Endies blog posts.</p>
<p><em>Edit: apparently my blog’s template doesn’t play nice with how I wrote this post, so please forgive some of the formatting!</em></p>
<h2 id="the-stats">The Stats</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Game</th>
<th>Sessions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Triangle Agency</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frontier Scum</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liminal Horror</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brindlewood Bay</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cairn</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Yazeba’s</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Trophy Dark</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Troika</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Zone</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Vessel</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tarot Heist</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stay Frosty</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Shadowdark</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pathfinder 2E</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patchwork World</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Paranoia</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OVER/UNDER</td>
<td>1*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oddfolk</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Legend in the Mist</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Himbos of Myth and Mettle</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hearts of Wulin</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dolmenwood</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dating.Sim</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Daggerheart</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><small>*I was only lightly engaged in OVER/UNDER, so I’m calling it one session. You could easily also call it 30 sessions.</small></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Role</th>
<th>Sessions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Player</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GM</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GMless</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Solo</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="the-superlatives">The Superlatives</h2>
<p><strong>Inspired the biggest thoughts about my life:</strong> <a href="https://samsorensen.blot.im/mothership-month-2025-wargame-over/under">OVER/UNDER</a></p>
<p>If you’re at all on RPG social media, I’m sure you heard about this. If not, it was a month-long, real-time megagame run on Discord by Sam Sorensen as part of Mothership Month. It was intended to be mostly a wargame/political megagame, and quickly transformed into a freewheeling larp. It was very weird and very cool and a very big time commitment to engage with fully. I only lightly participated, but the tension between how much I wanted to participate and how much I decided to participate <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com2025-11-10-should-and-want.html">inspired this post about “shoulds” and “wants”</a>. I want to stop holding myself back from the things I want! OVER/UNDER put this into sharp focus for me, and for that, it gets an Endie!</p>
<p><strong>Most resonant character:</strong> <a href="https://shop.hauntedtable.games/collections/games/products/triangle-agency-core-rulebook-preorder">Triangle Agency</a></p>
<p>Sorry. Couldn’t resist. Liv Butkiss, Clown, Romantic, Gun. Forever in my heart. I hope your romance with the White Whale anomaly gives you the thrill of the hunt, of longing, of flirting, of being right on the edge of a big breakthrough that changes mathematics forever, forever.</p>
<p>Triangle Agency is real good. It sounds like a lot to GM and I want to say thank you so much to <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/konahart.darlingbat.games">Kona</a> for GMing it! It was an RPG highlight of my year!</p>
<p><strong>Most frequently recommended</strong>: <a href="https://erinking.itch.io/patchwork-world-sixth-edition">Patchwork World</a></p>
<p>Whether you’re a hardcore PbtA-gead, just PbtA-curious, or don’t even know what PbtA is, I think you would get something out of playing or reading Patchwork World. Aaron King turns Moves into Poetry. It is a delight in play, and it is a delight to just read the moves and imagine the characters and worlds and play they suggest.</p>
<h2 id="intentions">Intentions</h2>
<p>A few intentions for 2026:</p>
<p><strong>Continue to explore solo RPGs!</strong> Inspired by an episode of <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/dungeon-module-2-140574494">Between Two Cairns</a> where Benjamin Marra and Sam Mameli talk about solo playing RPGs that aren’t designed to be solo RPGs. I’ve now played a few sessions of <a href="https://cairnrpg.com/">Cairn</a> solo, and it’s been a fascinating experience. I started off using <a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/en/product/522147/flint-a-cairn-2e-solo-handbook">Flint</a> as an oracle to support solo play, but have found myself relying on it less and less and simply using the core Cairn mechanics of Wilderness Travel procedures, reaction rolls, and the die of fate to inject some external input into my imagination.</p>
<p><strong>Transform GM prep into something I enjoy as a form of play in and of itself.</strong> I’m curious if solo RPGs will be a way to work on this. I’ve been working on reducing the amount of stress GM prep gives me, but I still have a complicated relationship with it, and it triggers a lot of baggage I carry regarding procrastination. I want GM prep to be something I <em>want</em> to do, not something that I am always wrestling with in the pile of things that I <em>should</em> do. The way playing Cairn solo has felt like it straddles the line between playing an RPG and prepping for a session of play feels fruitful. I’m also curious if I can use solo play as a form of writing to work on Kate and my next project in the FOLK series, The Sunset School for Girls.</p>
<p><strong>Cultivate intrinsic motivation for my RPG projects.</strong> Kate and I decided to pull out of doing Zine Month this upcoming February, and I’m excited and nervous about tackling The Sunset School for Girls without the external pressure of “the backers are depending on us.” This is a move towards the intrinsically motivated way I want to approach my art, but it is very different than the model of school assignments and clients that my education and professional life have revolved around.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! And if you have an end-of-year writeup, I’d love to read it! Shoot me an email at <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.commailto:brendan@brendanalbano.com">brendan@brendanalbano.com</a> with the link!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Should and Want</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-11-10-should-and-want.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-11-10-should-and-want.html</id>
    <published>2025-11-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on November 10, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Dear Reader, I haven’t done a big introspective post about my feelings in a while, but I’m feeling it tonight. So buckle up, or hit the eject button. If you’re still here, here’s what I’ve been thinking about:</p>
<p>I am infested with “should”s. They motivate my actions. They are the core of my judgments. “I should do this.” “I should not do that.” This infestation has been going on so long that its roots extend deep into the core of my identity.</p>
<p>I started paying attention to these “should”s a year or two ago (thanks therapy!), and at first, my main concern with them was that they made me feel bad. As I have increased my awareness of these “should”s and am learning to change the patterns of thinking that cause suffering, I have uncovered a much more insidious effect.</p>
<p>The “should”s, reasonable or otherwise, have taken up so much space in my brain they have edged out the “want”s. Not only do they edge them out, they also have a way of turning an activity that might start out with “I want to” into some sort of commitment that becomes “I should”. Sometimes the “should” is tied up in (perceived) commitments other people. Sometimes the “should” emerges because I have instrumentalized the activity. I’m no longer doing it because I want to, no longer doing it for the sake of doing it, instead I’m feeling like I “should” do it because it’s a step towards some other disconnected goal or reason or obligation.</p>
<p>And when I manage to clear away enough “should”s to make space for an “I want” it’s so quiet I can’t make out what it is that it’s saying. I do lots of things that I enjoy, but I feel adrift when I try to dig into thinking about what I want. Somehow it’s not quite the same. I feel out of practice. I want to be practiced at wanting! An expert wanter!</p>
<h3 id="a-brief-aside-on-the-like-button">A Brief Aside on the Like Button</h3>
<p>One “want” that has not been pushed aside by the mountain of “should”s is the desire for social validation. I have stopped using most forms of social media because I get addicted to the hits of social validation in a way that ultimately makes me feel bad.</p>
<p>Even on those that I still use (Discord), I feel an addictive pull towards firing off a clever comment or a useful piece of advice, and then anxiously awaiting a reaction emoji or reply.</p>
<p>“Wanting” these tiny hits of low-stakes social validation is a “want” I don’t feel out of practice at. Although I do feel like it is in its most ultra-processed, low-nutrition form when it is expressed by wanting emoji reacts.</p>
<h2 id="rediscovering-i-want">Rediscovering “I Want”</h2>
<p>I have developed a three-part plan to become an expert wanter, consisting of: secrets, mindfulness, and obsession. I will develop a secret hobby, I will engage in mindfulness, and I will say yes to getting obsessed. I suspect this “plan” will evolve as I continue to explore these ideas, but it felt good to write it up in my web journal to help clarify my thinking.</p>
<h3 id="secret-hobby">Secret Hobby</h3>
<p>My first strategy was to start a secret hobby. The two requirements for this hobby were:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It can’t be directly useful for my work or my art practice.</li>
<li>I can’t tell anybody what it is.</li>
</ol>
<p>It’s not instrumental, it’s not for something else, and I can’t get social kudos by telling people about it. (Even telling people I <em>have</em> a secret hobby is probably dubious, but I’m relying on the fact that this blog doesn’t have comments to smooth over that aspect.)</p>
<p>The purpose of doing the secret hobby is to do the secret hobby (thanks Thich Nhat Hanh).</p>
<p>Making a list of secret hobby options was a lot of fun. Picking my secret hobby was remarkably difficult. The one I picked was one of the ones that I felt most resistant to <em>and</em> is something that I’ve wanted to get into many times in the past and have chosen not to because I didn’t have a good reason besides “I want to.” I’ve been at it about a month now, and it’s incredibly liberating for the only reason I’m doing it to be “I want to.”</p>
<h3 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h3>
<p>Practicing mindfulness serves two purposes in this effort. First, through paying attention to my thoughts, I notice when I am thinking “I should do this” or when I am thinking “I want to do this.” I notice how I feel when I think those thoughts. I noticed what I was doing before I thought those thoughts, and I will notice what I do after I think those thoughts.</p>
<p>Second, the emphasis on paying attention <em>non-judgmentally</em> is critical to escape the trap of “I should be thinking ‘I want’.” One of the reasons “should” is so tricky is because I am so used to it being the way I motivate myself to do things. I don’t want to be paying attention to my thoughts, notice that I have been thinking “I should” and then pile onto myself with a “I shouldn’t be thinking I should.” That’s where the emphasis on non-judgment is useful.</p>
<p>Increasing my awareness though meditation practice helps me to be more mindful more often.</p>
<h3 id="obsession">Obsession</h3>
<p>I love to get obsessed. I love to dig deep into a new interest. And yet I find that so often I hold myself back. I’m writing this as the month-long play-by-post mega-game OVER/UNDER is wrapping up. OVER/UNDER was a lot of things, but for this post the two most relevant things are: 1. I thought it was really cool and 2. to really engage with it required devoting a ton of time to it.</p>
<p>I frequently found myself thinking “I wish I could clear my schedule and fully dive into this wild game, instead of mostly being a lurker.”</p>
<p>The thing is, I have a great deal of control over my schedule. I <em>could</em> have cleared my schedule enough to fully dive in. But I didn’t. I held back. I wasn’t sure if I “should”.</p>
<p>I don’t want to hold back! I want to chase a flight of fancy in a mad, breathless, dash, even if I trip over some roots along the way. I want to stop letting the fancies fly past as I hem and haw about whether or not I “should” chase them.</p>
<p>I’m not sure what the next thing will be, but when I feel the tug, I will say yes! I will buy a new notebook for this new obsession and fill it with my experiences.</p>
<h3 id="finally">Finally</h3>
<p>I’m still not clear why it feels like there is such a big difference between all the things that I do that I genuinely enjoy doing, and this amorphous idea that I am struggling with being able to put a clear shape to the things that I want. But it feels like there is something there, and I am excited about my secret hobby, and I’m excited about saying yes to new obsessions. And if you’ve read this far, I’m excited you’ve come along for the ride. If any of this resonates with you, I hope these rambles have given you something interesting to think about!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>More than telling a story part 1 - Describing</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-10-04-more-than-telling-a-story-part-1-describing.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-10-04-more-than-telling-a-story-part-1-describing.html</id>
    <published>2025-10-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-10-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on October  4, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>When I hear people say what they like about RPGs, oftentimes it’s something along the lines of “it’s fun to tell stories with your friends.” And while I love stories, and I enjoy the stories that emerge from playing RPGs, sometimes I find centering the idea of <em>telling</em> a story a little stressful. I think this is because I create a pressure on myself to “do good writing.” Perhaps I can learn to stop putting this pressure on myself. Becoming aware of and changing my relationship with the pressures I put on myself is an ongoing project ;).</p>
<p>In the meantime, I’ve been thinking about the things I like about RPGs that aren’t “telling a story.” A story will tend to emerge from these things, because they usually involve events happening in sequence, but I find it exciting to release the intention of <em>telling</em> a story.</p>
<p>I’m going to experiment with doing a blog series where I post about things I enjoy in RPGs that aren’t “telling a story.” The first one is “describing.”</p>
<h3 id="describing">Describing</h3>
<p>I watched <em>Barbarella</em> for the first time recently, and then proceeded to listen to a bunch of podcasts about <em>Barbarella</em>. I had an “aha!” moment listening to the <em>Midnight Mass</em> podcast, Episode 39, <em>Barbarella</em>, where they said “[<em>Barbarella</em> is] more about these extravagant set pieces and these strange sequences that further push you into a non-reality than any really structured plot… it’s a bunch of just scenes until the plot sort of happens, but each of those scenes are sort of their own draggy experiences.”</p>
<figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2025-10-04-more-than-telling-a-story-part-1-describing/barbarella-essence-of-man.jpg" alt="Essence of Man" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Essence of Man</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Just like the extravagant set pieces and strange sequences in <em>Barbarella</em>, there is a playful joy in simply describing wild shit. Whether it’s a setting, a situation, or a creature, I relish the creative act of describing. This can be a special treat for the GM, or something the whole table contributes to, depending on the style of game. The describing can be conjured up wholly from your imagination, a response to a prompt, or filling in the blanks in something from an adventure module. I have found great satisfaction in treating this act of describing as play in-and-of-itself, rather than as something in service to another goal, such as telling a story.</p>
<p>This is one of the things I love about GMing <a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/en/product/373291/mouth-brood"><em>Mouth Brood</em></a> by Amanda Lee Franck. The module has you constantly describing environments full of strange plants and animals, then rolling a random encounter with an animal, that has a random behavior, that may involve it interacting with another random animal. Ingesting that series of nested prompts and then launching into a description of what’s happening that weaves them all together puts me into a locked-into-the-present-moment state where everything else falls away. I love it.</p>
<p>I also found the procedure for <a href="https://cairnrpg.com/second-edition/wardens-guide/dungeon-seeds/#creating-a-dungeon">creating a dungeon</a> in the Cairn 2E Warden’s Guide to scratch a similar itch. Describing the dungeon, and then describing the individual rooms of the dungeon, all responding to prompts from two-column spark tables, was an absolute delight. Both in describing them to myself as I wrote my notes, and in describing them to my players during the session.</p>
<p>A final example, for players this time, is the joy of describing what your character is wearing. There is a delightful example of this in the <em>Dimension 20</em> actual play “A Court of Fey and Flowers” where Oscar Montoya has so much fun describing his character’s outfit, and the rest of the cast have so much fun listening to the description, that it becomes a recurring element that is repeated every episode. Not every character has as deep and fantastical of a closet as Oscar’s character Delloso de la Rue, but I’ve enjoyed it every time I pause for a moment to describe the appearance, the posture, the movement, the smell, the sound of my character, their clothes, or their equipment.</p>
<p>Next time you’re playing a game, you might try being mindful of opportunities for description. If you start describing something, and it feels like it’s starting to resonate, dive in! Let everything else fall away, and get wild with description.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Your Poetry will be Remembered for Countless Generations (Playtest)</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-09-10-your-poetry-will-be-remembered-for-countless-generations-playtest.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-09-10-your-poetry-will-be-remembered-for-countless-generations-playtest.html</id>
    <published>2025-09-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-09-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on September 10, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>In this game you create a character and write poems as that character. Perform Part 1 once to create a character. Repeat Part 2 each time you write a poem as that character. Roll a 6-sided die to select a result from the numbered lists.</p>
<h2 id="part-1-who-are-you">Part 1: Who are you?</h2>
<p>You are a scholar and a</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Bureaucrat</li>
<li>Merchant</li>
<li>Warrior</li>
<li>Artisan</li>
<li>Doctor</li>
<li>Hunter</li>
</ol>
<p>Your world is one of</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Instability</li>
<li>Technology</li>
<li>Scarcity</li>
<li>Abundance</li>
<li>Hierarchy</li>
<li>Nomads</li>
</ol>
<p>&amp;</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Spirits</li>
<li>Philosophy</li>
<li>Heroes</li>
<li>Decay</li>
<li>Intrigue</li>
<li>Love</li>
</ol>
<p>Your poetry will be remembered for countless generations.</p>
<h2 id="part-2-what-is-the-context-in-which-this-poem-found-you">Part 2: What is the context in which this poem found you?</h2>
<p>To write a poem, roll on the following tables to determine the context in which the poem found you. Then write the poem.</p>
<p>Repeat Part 2 every day for a week, rolling a new context and writing a new poem each day. Any amount of time may pass within the fiction between the poems.</p>
<p>If you’re not sure where to start, try writing four lines. They don’t have to rhyme. You don’t have to reference the context in your poem; it is enough to be aware of it.</p>
<h3 id="you-have-been">You have been</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Writing poetry</li>
<li>Traveling to visit a friend</li>
<li>High</li>
<li>Sick</li>
<li>Working</li>
<li>Outside</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="it-is">It is</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Raining</li>
<li>Buggy</li>
<li>Snowing</li>
<li>Hot</li>
<li>Perfect</li>
<li>A full moon</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-sense-you-have-been-meditating-on-is">The sense you have been meditating on is</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Smell</li>
<li>Taste</li>
<li>Tough</li>
<li>Hearing</li>
<li>Sight</li>
<li>Self-awareness</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-poem-found-you-via">The poem found you via</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>A person</li>
<li>A place</li>
<li>A thing</li>
<li>An idea</li>
<li>An emotion</li>
<li>Inexplicably</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="a-note-to-playtesters">A note to playtesters</h2>
<p>Thank you for playtesting this game! I’d love to hear about your experience. If there were any parts that resonated with you or that you struggled with, please call them out. If you’d like to share the poems, I’d be thrilled to read them. Your feedback is much appreciated. Playtest reports can be sent to <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.commailto:brendan@kb-ba.com">brendan@kb-ba.com</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>FWD Retreat Mini-con Reflections</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-04-14-fwd-retreat-mini-con-reflections.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-04-14-fwd-retreat-mini-con-reflections.html</id>
    <published>2025-04-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-04-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on April 14, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I just got back from a mini-con/GM retreat and wanted to jot down some highlights and reflections before I have to do my chores and get back to the office!</p>
<p>This is now the 2nd year that about 15 of the folks who run games for <a href="https://fwdrpg.org/">FWD RPG PNW</a> have rented out a building at the Mt. Hood Kiwanis Camp to have a weekend of gaming and chatting and snacking. This year we expanded the amount of gaming space we rented, which ended up including a fireplace and a surprise guest (more on that in a second), and it was delightful! There’s something special about playing games <em>on vacation</em> that feels different than playing games on a weekend. Even if the “vacation” is just a long weekend. I highly recommend it!</p>
<h2 id="mouth-brood">Mouth Brood</h2>
<p>On Friday night, I ran <a href="https://gamesomnivorous.com/collections/manifestus-omnivorous/products/mouth-brood">Mouth Brood</a> by <a href="https://comradery.co/amandalee">Amanda Lee Franck</a>. I think the print version is out of print, but I got a PDF from <a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/en/product/373291/mouth-brood">Drive Thru RPG</a>. This was my second time running Mouth Brood, and it delivered again. The players spent the first half of the session nervously scoping out the site, setting traps and trying to lure creatures out rather than venture into the unknown. I was at first worried that this might not be fun, but the magic of these site-based, “plotless” modules is that they can accommodate unexpected ways of engaging with the adventure site. The tension of watching and waiting turned out to be really fun and made it all the more exciting when the players finally braved entering the dome buried in the glacier.</p>
<p>An unexpected highlight was the arrival of this beautiful eldritch creature just as the team first encountered a cat-like monster:</p>
<figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2025-04-14-fwd-retreat-mini-con-reflections/grey-kitty.jpg" alt="Grey Kitty" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Grey Kitty</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>In a beautiful moment of foreshadowing, our new friend took a liking to the player (who took this photo) who’s character was the first to be torn apart by the cat-creature.</p>
<p>We used <a href="https://liminalhorrorrpg.com/">Liminal Horror</a> as the system to run this system-agnostic module, and I thought it worked well to have the system take the back seat and let the module itself shine. I remain a huge fan of both Mouth Brood and Amanda Lee Franck.</p>
<h2 id="paranoia">Paranoia</h2>
<p>Saturday morning I played in a game of <a href="https://www.mongoosepublishing.com/collections/paranoia">Paranoia</a>, which has been on my “want to play” list for ages. It was a blast. I really enjoyed the character creation process where the choices I made impacted the other player’s character sheet, and vice versa. It felt like a fun mix of the best parts of getting to make a character from scratch, and the best parts of being handed a randomly generated character to respond to.</p>
<p>The GM had prepared a lot of great stuff for the scenario, including a huge pile of fortune-cookie-sized slips of paper with the “threat analysis messages” that were being delivered by a helmet that was assigned to the other player’s troubleshooter when we set out on our job. After getting more and more worried about the mountain of secret information the GM was passing to the other player, it was revealed about half-way through the scenario that these were randomly generated corporate platitudes and encouragements. Not sinister threat analysis data at all. Except the one time they were. Delightful.</p>
<p>I’m glad to have played Paranoia, I’d play it again, and I had a ton of fun with just 1 GM and 2 players.</p>
<h2 id="patchwork-world">Patchwork World</h2>
<p>On Saturday evening I ran <a href="https://erinking.itch.io/patchwork-world-sixth-edition">Patchwork World</a> by Aaron King. I ran the free pamphlet version of <a href="https://roll4tarrasque.itch.io/baktos-terrifying-cuisine">Bakto’s Terrifying Cuisine</a> by Giuliano Roverato. I’ve come to realize that 1 double-sided 8.5x11 piece of paper is exactly how much content I want for a one-shot, so Bakto’s was perfect.</p>
<p>The stripped-down, PbtA, all-moves nature of Patchwork World made running the one-shot easy and fun for me, and my players told me they particularly loved the way character creation worked. The first thing we did in character creation was each player picked two moves from the long list of wonderfully unhinged moves. Then, the alchemy of placing the two moves side-by-side magically generated a character concept that drove the rest of character creation. It was easy, and more importantly, it was fun!</p>
<p>My partner said that this is the first time she felt like she’s really gotten how moves can be cool and fun in a PbtA game. It’s not the first time I’ve tried to explain what is cool and fun about them, so credit goes to Aaron King for this brilliant meditation on moves!</p>
<h2 id="legend-in-the-mist">Legend in the Mist</h2>
<p>In what became a theme of the weekend for me, character creation was a lot of fun. Characters in <a href="https://cityofmist.co/collections/legend-in-the-mist">Legend in the Mist</a> are primarily composed of 4 themes, and the GM had pre-generated a big stack of themes, with a set of “kid” themes (since we were all playing teenagers), plus a bunch of others. Coming up with a concept first, then making up 4 themes to flesh it out would have been an analysis-paralysis-fueled nightmare.</p>
<p>Instead, I had the joy of choosing sparks from a thoughtfully curated pile one by one and watching a character emerge.</p>
<p>First I chose “bookworm” as my kid theme since it called out to me and I was feeling a little self-insert-y. Then I picked “expert skulker,” imagining a slightly creepy bookworm who also read the world like a book, sneaking and hiding and watching. Then it all came together when I picked “aspiring blade.” While, yes, I was setting up a “while you were out kissing, I studied the blade” joke, I think the reason that joke resonates so well is because we (or maybe I should just speak for myself) see ourselves in the nerd who studied the blade. I felt like Tud “Threnadir” Ladley blossomed into an endearing and full-formed character that was a delight to inhabit. Lastly, I picked “tenacious” which added a fun balance to the downside “my asthma!” that I got by picking bookworm. It seemed like the other players had an equally delightful journey through picking their themes.</p>
<p>I think the game system itself is probably not exactly what I’m looking for, but it had a lot of bits I enjoyed, and I had a blast being a fantasy teenager at magical summer camp.</p>
<h2 id="the-zone">The Zone</h2>
<p>As a nice thematic bookend to the weekend, which began with the Roadside Picnic inspired OSR module Mouth Brood, the last game I played was the Roadside Picnic inspired storygame <a href="https://thezonerpg.com/">The Zone</a> by Raph D’Amico. I haven’t read Roadside Picnic, but I’ve had it on hold at the library for a while, and I came home to an email that it had arrived!</p>
<p>Character creation in The Zone also involved selecting a few prompts to combine into a character. Somehow this didn’t have quite the alchemy for me that Patchwork World and Legend in the Mist did, but this very well may be because I was pretty tired at this point. It’s also possible that the prompts themselves didn’t resonate with me personally as much as the previous two games did. I still think it’s a good design, and made sense for this game.</p>
<p>If you know you like, or are at all curious about GM-less horror games, The Zone is well worth checking out. I had a great time playing it, although I don’t know that I’ll be rushing out to replay it. I thought the design felt really smart, but I’m not a huge horror-head, so perhaps the themes of obsession and phobia didn’t grab me as much as they do some people.</p>
<p>I also think I tend to like GM-ed games slightly more than GM-less games, although it’s not a hard rule. I do <em>love</em> describing weird shit, and that’s basically the core gameplay loop, so that really worked for me.</p>
<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>
<ul>
<li>Character creation that involves picking 2-4 items from an evocative list of prompts and finding out what sort of character emerges rules. More of that please!</li>
<li>Having to prep your game in between playing games because you didn’t get a chance to do it before the con is kind of a bummer for me. So note-to-self: either bring prepless games, or do 100% of your prep beforehand.</li>
<li>Sitting around chatting after the last game of the day remains one of my favorite parts of a con. Making sure to have finished my prep would have allowed even more of this unstructured relaxing time, so more of that please!</li>
</ul>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Storygame Rumors for Challenge-based Play</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-02-12-storygame-rumors-for-challenge-based-play.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-02-12-storygame-rumors-for-challenge-based-play.html</id>
    <published>2025-02-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on February 12, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I’m currently running a campaign of Frontier Scum and last session I started a hexcrawl using the procedures in the Games Omniverious Hexcrawl Toolkit. Part of that procedure involves coming up with a list of rumors, and I thought to myself, “I love the rumors phase in Good Society, what if I just ask my players to provide the rumors?”</p>
<p>We’ve added a phase of play to our campaign that I’m calling “Around the Campfire” where I ask the players to respond to prompts (either in character, or narrating their character’s thoughts) whenever they are sitting around a campfire eating their beans. For the Around the Campfire before they set off on their hexcrawl, I asked them to each tell me a rumor they’d heard about one of the hexes on the table.</p>
<p>It turned out to be really fun! It got everyone much more invested in the broader hex map beyond their immediate destination, and it fueled some good discussion about which route to take, because they were excited about the rumors they had created.</p>
<p>One of the things that I thought let this storygame/writer’s-room-style moment of having the players make up things about the world fit into our mostly OSR-style game is that because they are rumors, they are both diagetic things that their characters could know, and they might not be true.</p>
<p>In the recent episode of Between Two Cairns “The Smoking Pillar of Lan Yu”, Yochai Gal talks about the the tension between storygame-style shared narrative authorship, and OSR-style challenge-based play. If as a player you are empowered to make up things about the world, it’s hard to feel like you have to use your wits to pilot your character through overcoming a challenge, because you can just invent a fact about the world that solves the problem.</p>
<p>However, my players and I, quite enjoy sharing the storygame-style ability to invent things about the world! By positioning these things as rumors, rather than truths, the GM still has the final say about the nature of the challenges that the players and their characters will need to overcome, but it also allows us to play in the space of shared authorship that we quite enjoy.</p>
<p>Try giving your players an opportunity to make up rumors about the world! I found it to be really fun and create a lot of engagement with the world without sacrificing the central challenge-based mode of play in my OSR game. If you do, I’d love to hear how it goes!</p>
<p>And as a little visual treat, here are some of lovely hexes from <a href="https://gamesomnivorous.com/collections/hex-omnivorous">Games Omniverious</a></p>
<figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2025-02-12-storygame-rumors-for-challenge-based-play/rotten-springs-hexcrawl.jpg" alt="Rotten Springs Hexcrawl" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Rotten Springs Hexcrawl</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>They’re headed to Rotten Springs. If you’d like to take a dip in Rotten Springs yourself, pick up <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/rotten-springs">Gurtie’s Guide VII - Rotten Springs</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. if it’s still February 2025, go check out Kate and my project <a href="https://www.backerkit.com/c/projects/kb-ba/folk-volume-ii?ref=brendanalbanocom">FOLK Volume II: Travelers of the Inky Void on Backerkit!</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2024, A Year of Play</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-01-04-2024-a-year-of-play.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2025-01-04-2024-a-year-of-play.html</id>
    <published>2025-01-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2025-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on January  4, 2025
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I didn’t realize it as it was happening, or really until I sat down to write a post reflecting on 2024, but it turns out it was a year of a lot of firsts for me! No wonder I feel so wrung out!</p>
<p>I’m going to briefly mention one work first, which is that construction has begun on Kate and my first project as KB+BA Architecture. But I have a lot of complicated feelings about architecture right now and want to use this post to focus on some RPG firsts!</p>
<h2 id="word-wizards">Word Wizards</h2>
<p>I was shocked to see that according to itch.io, I published <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/word-wizards">Word Wizards</a> on May 26, 2024. I thought surely I published this in 2023, making 2024 a garbage year where I accomplished nothing creatively. But in fact, 2024 was the year where I published my very first roleplaying game! I will be telling my therapist about this miraculous discovery.</p>
<p>I want to give a big thank you to my friends Andy, Lex and Braden, since our informal “hey, what if we all met up once a week to encourage each other to work on our game design projects” was what made Word Wizards happen!</p>
<p>Since we’ve got a therapy sub-theme going on in this post, 2024 was a big success regarding my goal of becoming a game designer. In fact, I have fully accomplished this goal, because I have designed a game. Believe you me gentle reader, I want to move these goalposts so bad, but I’m not going to. (At least not while you are watching me!)</p>
<p>In 2025 I’m looking forward to another round of playtesting, revising and publishing finished versions of two projects I released as playtests/beta versions in 2024: <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/eyambf-playtest">Everything You Are Must Be Found</a> and <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/every-knights-story-begins">Every Knight’s Story Begins</a>.</p>
<h2 id="my-first-con">My First Con</h2>
<p>Kate and I attended two RPG cons this year, something neither of us had done before! The first, making it my first con, was <a href="https://goplaynw.org/">Go Play NW</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to playing lots of games, Go Play’s format of organizing games via <a href="https://goplaynw.org/the-donut/">The Donut</a> made it a great, low-pressure environment to run some games as well! I had a lot of fun running Mausritter and Electric Bastionland.</p>
<p>Go Play is a relatively small con, and it was a good way to ease myself into the con experience before attending Big Bad Con later in the year. Which I understand isn’t even that big by con standards?! Regardless, the games were lovely, and even more lovely were the between-game and late-night conversations and camaraderie of a whole bunch of people coming together to celebrate something they are extremely passionate about.</p>
<h2 id="my-first-time-tabling">My First Time Tabling</h2>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="https://www.bigbadcon.com/">Big Bad Con</a> Small Press Showcase, Kate and I got a chance to table and sell our zines for the first time! Kate’s project <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/folk">FOLK</a> was our flagship product (if you’re in Portland, you can probably snag a print copy at Board Bard Games, Dark Future, or Secret Room), but I had a blast hawking my wares as well, including a <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/can-we-keep-it">“shitpost game”</a> I made at a Big Bad Con workshop and printed on the hotel printer. All the other folks selling games were so enthusiastic and supportive, and trading zines with everyone was a con highlight.</p>
<h2 id="a-year-of-play">A Year of Play</h2>
<p>In <em>Rules of Play</em>, Salen and Zimmerman propose “Play is free movement within a more rigid structure” (p. 304) as a definition of play, and it has really resonated with me. I find it useful to ask “what is the free movement?” and “what is the rigid structure?” These questions have been useful to me in thinking about formal games, but lately I am also intrigued by using this definition and these questions as a way to approach life more playfully.</p>
<p>One of the projects I want to work on in 2025 is investing significant time into working on our house. House projects have been overwhelming, and I’m curious if I can change my relationship with working on the house by approaching it through this lens of play. I’m calling it “playing house.” Hopefully I’ll have some updates on this project throughout the year!</p>
<h2 id="some-favorites-of-2024">Some Favorites of 2024</h2>
<p>Not necessarily things that came out in 2024, just some things I loved in 2024! I feel like I’m forgetting a zillion things, but I gotta stop somewhere.</p>
<ul>
<li>My Favorite Thing Is Monsters Vol. 2 by Emil Ferris</li>
<li>Coyote Doggirl by Lisa Hanawalt</li>
<li>Adventure Hooks by Tyler Crumrine</li>
<li>Jeremiah Brent on Queer Eye Season 9</li>
<li><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/rtfm/id1555180427">RTFM Podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/malpractice.pdx/">Malpractice</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.tpkbrewing.com/">TPK Brewing</a></li>
<li>The glass cups that cortados come in</li>
<li>Sauna and Spa at Everett House</li>
<li>The Mt. Tabor Red Loop</li>
<li>Dog watching</li>
</ul>
<p>Wishing you a playful 2025!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>REEL Robot Fishing</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-12-22-reel-robot-fishing.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-12-22-reel-robot-fishing.html</id>
    <published>2024-12-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-12-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on December 22, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I had a fantastic time playing Reel Robot Fishing (Solo Version) by Sandro AD for Prismatic Wasteland’s Covert Critic Secret Santa 2024. What follows is a transcript of my play session! I hope you enjoy fishing with Peregrine Nova and The Goblin as much as I did!</p>
<p>Download <a href="https://sandroad.itch.io/reel-robot-fishing">Reel Robot Fishing on itch.</a></p>
<h2 id="character-creation">Character Creation</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pilot: Peregrine Nova</li>
<li>MEC (Mobile Engagement Chassis) Tag: The Goblin</li>
<li>Edges
<ul>
<li>MEC: Hit-and-run, Ambush</li>
<li>Pilot: Reading the battlefield</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Threats
<ul>
<li>MEC: Small, Non-standard tech</li>
<li>Pilot: Impatient</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Gear
<ul>
<li>Gyroscopic auto-thrusters</li>
<li>Javelin-class Swarm Hive</li>
<li>REEL (Robustly Engineered Electronic Line)</li>
<li>Plenty of snacks</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="reel-robot-fishing">REEL Robot Fishing</h2>
<h3 id="cast-1">Cast 1</h3>
<ul>
<li>Nothing Bites (d4 landed outside the prompts)</li>
<li>Topic of Reflection: Recount a cherished memory that involves a usual or past companion.</li>
</ul>
<p>My REEL flies deep into the inky abyss. I’m warm in my MEC, despite the temperature outside hovering around 8°C. Nothing is biting. I drift into memory. The last time I visited the stormy waters of Yorin Gamma I’d just graduated from MEC academy. Leigh and I had cut each other’s hair that night. I’d forgotten what we caught, or if we even caught anything, but the impromptu haircut I remembered in perfect detail.</p>
<h3 id="cast-2">Cast 2</h3>
<ul>
<li>Nothing Bites (d4 landed outside the prompts)</li>
<li>Topic of Reflection: What is your favorite childhood memory?</li>
</ul>
<p>Not much in the water this morning. But plenty in my head apparently. I remember swimming in the warm waters of the Betyllion Sea. I was 8 and it was the first time I had ever been on a vacation. The tour guide on the cruise explained that scientists had used brain scanners to determine that the seaweed here was sentient, but had never figured out how to communicate with it. The dappled light was mesmerizing. I never wanted come up. I could see why the seaweed didn’t care to have a conversation. Eventually my parents reeled me back in with the safety line on my kids diving suit because it was time for lunch.</p>
<h3 id="cast-3">Cast 3</h3>
<ul>
<li>Nothing Bites (d4 landed outside the prompts)</li>
<li>Topic of Reflection: What is something you have never told anyone?</li>
</ul>
<p>I guess there’s a reason Yorin Gamma isn’t a popular fishing destination. As the black waves crash over the side of the small ship I chartered it occurs to me that I feel relaxed. At peace. I don’t think I’ve ever told anyone, but I’m scared almost all the time. Is it what makes me a good MEC pilot? I hope not. I try not to think about it too much and focus on the fact that for a rare moment, out on this stormy sea alone, the fear is gone.</p>
<h3 id="cast-4">Cast 4</h3>
<ul>
<li>Nothing Bites (d4 landed ambiguously on a line)</li>
<li>Topic of Reflection: What has been your favorite place you have traveled to?</li>
</ul>
<p>The bobber jiggles, but no bite. My HUD shows something investigating the lure at the end of my REEL, but it doesn’t bite. I set my MEC’s arms to autopilot temporarily and retract my arms from the control sleeves. Like most MECs, The Goblin can carry out basic tasks by itself, but obviously that would be missing the point. But I take advantage of the the capability so that I can unwrap a MostMost brand Bourbon Bean Cake. Ubiquitous on the rim, but hard to find in Union space. I think about the furthest out I’d ever been. In my dossier the planet had just been identified by a 16 digit ID code, and my mouth didn’t have the right parts to say the name the locals called it. This was well past the part of the rim where you could find MostMost’s intoxicating snack cakes. I’ve never been able to put into words what it was about that place that stole my heart, but I’m pretty sure if I made a top 10 list of my favorite places I’d ever been, they’d be in order of how far out they were.</p>
<h3 id="cast-5">Cast 5</h3>
<ul>
<li>Something Nimble Bites!
<ul>
<li>The Catch has many dexterous tendrils</li>
<li>Two Successes needed to catch</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>The line snaps taught and I shove the bean cake into my mouth and slam my arms back into The Goblin’s control sleeves. The synthetic bourbon makes my eyes water. I may regret my choice of snack tomorrow.</p>
<p>Whatever has bit is a fast moving mess of tentacles. It pulls hard and my gyroscopic auto-thrusters activate to keep me upright. Then as quick as it pulled it reverses and charges the ship.</p>
<ul>
<li>Roll 2d6: 5 (+1 hit and run, -1 small); Failure</li>
</ul>
<p>The catch leaps out of the water, flying a good 3 meters over The Goblin’s cockpit. The creature is a ball of hundreds of scintillating purple tentacles, almost as big as my MEC. As it flies overhead, force vectors stream directly into my neural link and and I hit the emergency disconnect on my REEL before it hits the end of the line and yanks me into the water.</p>
<ul>
<li>Topic of Reflection: What is something that you would like to do with your MEC?</li>
</ul>
<p>I can’t help but laugh. Maybe it’s the synthetic alcohol, but th idea of reeling in that majestic and monstrous creature makes me laugh until I feel tears streaming down my face.</p>
<p>The AI systems in our MECs are designed not to exhibit any form of personality, but I know they used to and it ended up being a logistical nightmare for the Union. Even so, I feel myself wondering what sort of vacation The Goblin would enjoy. I should probably keep that thought to myself during the post-vacation debrief. I’ve only got one more tour on this contract, then I’m back to being a free agent again. I’ve heard rumors of freelancers unlocking the AI cores on their MECs, but always in the form of cautionary tales. I eat another Bourbon Bean Cake, accepting the hangover, and set a course back to shore.</p>
<h2 id="a-quick-review">A quick review</h2>
<p>Did this game turn me into a fan of journaling games, mechs and fishing all at once? Maybe it’s the bean cake talking, but I think it might have. The dexterity game portion where you throw the d4 onto the board to see what’s biting was harder than I expected, and that ended up working fantastically to reinforce the “fishing is really about sitting and thinking” theme. I was glad to have so few bites and so much time to explore my character! The structure of the game made me feel supported in conjuring up a universe and a character that I want to spend more time with, and that’s everything I want from a game! Thanks to Sandro AD for making such a delightful game, and thanks to Prismatic Wasteland for organizing the Covert Critic event that let me discover such a lovely game!</p>
<h2 id="links">Links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.prismaticwasteland.com/">Prismatic Wasteland</a>, host of the Covert Critic Secret Santa event. Thanks for organizing such a fun holiday event!</li>
<li><a href="https://sandroad.itch.io/">Sandro AD’s itch.io page</a>, with Reel Robot Fishing and many other cool games!</li>
<li><a href="https://robinfj.substack.com/i/152929417/prismatic-wasteland-secret-santa-covert-critic">Robin Fjärem’s review of one of my games for Covert Critic 2024!</a></li>
</ul>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Big Bad Con 2024</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-10-30-big-bad-con-2024.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-10-30-big-bad-con-2024.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-10-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on October 30, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I’m swimming in a hazy mixture of post-con-blues and invigorating enthusiasm after coming home from Big Bad Con. This was my second RPG con, and first “big” RPG con, and it was awesome. This post is a recap of what I did for my own memory, with a few thoughts at the end.</p>
<h2 id="games-played">Games Played</h2>
<ul>
<li>A Blade Breaks (playtest): had a blast narrating rad fight scenes. All those years of binge watching kung-fu movies paid off in this game.</li>
<li>Old School Essentials: lovely dungeon crawling shenanigans. The GM was great at encouraging and rewarding creative problem solving. Descending AC is silly, but I enjoyed experiencing it for historical purposes.</li>
<li>2 LARPs from the Golden Cobras: my first LARPs! I got to be a duck and a child who didn’t want to go to bed. I’m excited to bring my burgeoning clown practice and LARPs together. I think this is rich territory to explore.</li>
<li>Thirsty Sword Lesbians: smooched a witch. It was fun to play a romance game coming hot on the heels of a panel about romance in RPGs.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="panels-and-workshops">Panels and Workshops</h2>
<ul>
<li>Rise and Design with the Bakers: freeform Q&amp;A with Meguey Baker.</li>
<li>Roll to Kiss: romance in RPGs. I think my biggest takeaway was the comment to check in with yourself, in addition to checking in with your fellow players.</li>
<li>Shitpost TTRPG Design Workshop: a lovely encouragement to abandon caution and poop out a game, which I did!</li>
<li>The Play’s the Thing: RPG designers and dramaturgs talk about RPG design and dramaturgy.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="small-press-showcase">Small Press Showcase</h2>
<p>Kate and my first time tabling. We had a ton of fun sharing, selling, and trading our games:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/folk">FOLK</a></li>
<li><a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/eyambf-playtest">Everything You Are Must Be Found</a></li>
<li><a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/word-wizards">Word Wizards</a></li>
<li><a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/advanced-lasers-feelings">Advanced Lasers &amp; Feelings</a></li>
<li><a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/can-we-keep-it">Can We Keep It?</a> - Created at the Shitpost TTRPG Design Workshop and printed on the hotel printer!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conversations-and-community">Conversations and Community!</h2>
<p>This was the best part. Being immersed in the collective enthusiasm for play and games was cozy and inspiring. It felt like home. So many good ideas, bad ideas, good bad ideas, and so so many laughs. A heartfelt thank you to everyone I chatted with!</p>
<p>I’m looking forward to next year, looking forward to playing more games, running some games, and helping out with what will hopefully be the inaugural Big Bad Press zine tools corner so the person trimming their beautiful risograph zine doesn’t have to use the tiny, shitty scissors I happened to have in my first aid kit!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Goblin Ecology</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-10-12-goblin-ecology.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-10-12-goblin-ecology.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-10-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on October 12, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I love goblins. That itself is probably worthy of examination another time. But for today: why are goblins the way they are? I’m thinking particularly about goblins in the various flavors of fantasy RPGs I enjoy. In slightly older <a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/44996/goblin-market">stories about goblins</a>, goblins are like faeries, some combination of primordial force of trickery and metaphor, depending on the story.</p>
<p>But in modern RPGs, presumably drawing from Tolkien, goblins are earthly creatures that function ecologically.</p>
<p>I’m not sure where this came from, but I’ve had this thought kicking around in my head for quite a while, and it is time for it to be vomited forth: What if we apply a sci-fi-style “what if” lens to try to explain why goblins are the way they are?</p>
<p>What if goblin babies were completely self-sufficient from birth? Wikipedia tells me this is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Precociality_and_altriciality#Superprecociality">superprecociality</a>. A hatchling black mamba is capable of hunting prey the size of of a small rat. So too is the newborn goblin.</p>
<p>While a goblin could learn the value of community and care later in life, they do not begin their lives encountering these ideas through experiencing helplessness and dependence like a human baby. Nor do any goblins encounter these ideas due to the need for someone to parent baby goblins. What would this do to goblin society? Would goblins even have a communal society? Certainly I would expect it to be different than human society.</p>
<p>Can every goblin trope be explained by this superprecociality? Goblins as violent and untrustworthy? Sure. Goblins as bizarre and unique, each quirkier than the last? Sure! David Bowie as the Goblin King being fascinated by the helplessness of a human child? Absolutely!</p>
<p>Does this make goblins alien, tragic and morally ambiguous from a human perspective? Definitely. Does it take the easy, breezy fun away from them as quirky sidekicks or nameless canon-fodder? Probably. But that’s what you get trying to apply some trying-to-be-too-clever, sci-fi-style thinking to the lovable, horrible, little scamps!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Condition Critical</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-09-22-condition-critical.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-09-22-condition-critical.html</id>
    <published>2024-09-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on September 22, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>What would an OSR-style game look like without hit points (or wounds, or stress, or ruin, or any other similarly abstract resource)? What about without stats? I’ve been thinking about these questions because abstract ideas like hit points or stats are difficult to interact with within the fiction. And focusing on interacting with the fiction, rather than the numbers on your character sheet, is often cited as a component of OSR-style play.</p>
<p>What does it mean to interact with having 3 out of 10 hit points remaining? Or to interact with a Strength of 15? There’s a translation that has to occur to figure out what that is in the fiction. It’s not a terribly difficult translation, but it’s there nonetheless. So for this thought experiment, let’s assume we want to directly interact with fictional characteristics like “an arrow embedded in your shoulder” or “rippling with muscles”, while at the same time having clear mechanical effects for these characteristics. And we want to do it OSR-style, however ill-defined that may be. What might that look like?</p>
<p>We can look to the way games like <em>Blades in the Dark</em> and <em>Thirsty Sword Lesbians</em> use conditions to get one piece of the puzzle. Conditions are generally descriptions of bad things you are suffering from like “shot in the leg,” “drunk,” or “embarrassed”. Sometimes, like Harm in BitD, they are freeform, other times, like Conditions in TSL, they are a specific list. They also have some sort of mechanical effect, in addition to their narrative effects. Giving you a minus to your rolls, reducing the magnitude of your effects, reducing the size of your dice pool, etc.</p>
<p>What about no stats? Again, lots of great examples here, such as “Roll with the Questions” from <em>Pasión de las Pasiones</em>, or skills from <em>Trophy</em> (as just one of many examples of games that use a list of descriptive words as your skills).</p>
<p>But what about that impossible to define OSR vibe? One of the things I really enjoy in an OSR game is the fear, <a href="https://www.lines.com/glossary/sweat/1889">the sweat</a> (my new favorite term), that comes whenever the dice get rolled. I love the way damage works in games descended from Into the Odd. In particular, I love the way Critical Damage works, where when you take damage to your Strength score, you have to make a Strength Saving Throw, or suffer Critical Damage (which knocks you out of the fight, and is fatal if not tended to by your allies). Even a minor blow, a single point of strength damage, can take you out if you’re unlucky! Getting hurt is always risky and always scary. That feels very OSR to me. As an aside, the other thing I like about Critical Damage is that it’s high consequence, but usually doesn’t mean instant death as long as your allies are able to tend to your wounds before you expire.</p>
<p>Can I just squish Conditions and Critical Damage together and get everything I love about the <em>Into the Odd</em> Critical Damage roll without needing HP or a Strength score? I think yes! Here is a sketch of how this might work for a game I’m working on.</p>
<h2 id="conditions">Conditions</h2>
<p>Conditions are negative, ongoing effects like “shot in the leg,” “drunk,” “panicked,” etc. Conditions persist until they are removed by narrative means, such as receiving medical attention for a physical injury or finding a safe place to have someone help to calm you down if you are panicking.</p>
<p>Conditions impose -1d6 to dice rolls <em>(note: this is from a d6 dice pool game, but this can be easily adjusted to whatever dice system your game uses)</em> when they would impede the action you are performing. (If a condition would make the action impossible, you simply can’t do it.)</p>
<p>Typically, characters receive conditions as a result of rolling dice, but the GM may also assign conditions when it makes sense in the narrative.</p>
<h2 id="critical-damage">Critical Damage</h2>
<p>When you receive a new condition, roll a d6. If you roll equal to or under your number of conditions, you suffer Critical Damage.</p>
<p>Critical Damage is an amplified effect of the triggering condition that takes you out of action until you receive help. A physical injury might knock you out and leave you bleeding. Fear might cause you to flee in an uncontrolled panic. Embarrassment might result in you being completely unable to engage in the current social situation.</p>
<p>If you are not tended to within an hour or so, the Critical Damage becomes catastrophic. With a physical injury, this typically results in the character’s death, but other types of Critical Damage could result in your character fleeing forever, giving up the adventuring life and getting a real job, or otherwise being retired from play.</p>
<p>The GM may choose not to require a Critical Damage roll when a character receives a condition if it doesn’t make sense narratively: for example, a condition that came on slowly, or a condition where it doesn’t make sense for the condition to have a risk of knocking the character out of action.</p>
<p><strong>GM Tip:</strong> keep a notecard with a list of each character’s current conditions.</p>
<h3 id="variations-on-critical-damage">Variations on Critical Damage</h3>
<p>For a slightly more resilient characters, you can change the roll to “If you roll <del>equal to or</del> under your number of conditions, you suffer Critical Damage.” This means that the first condition you receive can’t trigger Critical Damage.</p>
<p>For a system that allows your characters to grow more resilient over time, or some characters to be more resilient than others, you can compare the number of Conditions to some other aspect of the character. For example, the game I’m working on has another characteristic called Cores, and the Critical Damage roll looks like this:</p>
<p>“When you receive a new Condition, if your number of Conditions exceeds your number of Cores, roll a d6. If you roll equal to or under the amount by which your number of conditions exceeds your number of cores, you suffer Critical Damage.”</p>
<p>The language gets a little clunky, but so far it’s felt good to have characters that have a clearer idea of who they are (by having more Cores) more likely to be able to find the will to power through their injuries rather than collapse.</p>
<h2 id="sparked-my-curiosity">Sparked my curiosity</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.inoreader.com/article/3a9c6e745f923313-clowns">Rise Up Comus</a> talks about clowns (which reminded me that I have the seed of an idea about a “solo clown LARP” that I want to return to)</li>
<li><a href="https://playfulvoid.game.blog/2024/06/06/thoughts-on-module-writing/">Playful Void</a> shares some thoughts on module writing</li>
</ul>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Mind the Salt</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-09-21-mind-the-salt.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-09-21-mind-the-salt.html</id>
    <published>2024-09-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-09-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on September 21, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>After lurking on my shelf for measureless eons, <em>Arkham Horror: The Card Game</em> has me back in its tentacles. This is mostly thanks to a friend getting really into it, buying all the cards, and carrying my along in his enthusiasm until it was too late for me. I can’t get enough of it. And playing once or twice a month when the four of us manage to align our schedules certainly isn’t enough. So I began playing solo.</p>
<p>The first thing I found is that playing solo analog games has been a great way to wind down in the evening. The second thing I found is that I get salty when the game doesn’t go my way. This surprised me. I think of myself as a non-salty gamer. Sweet, even. A good sport. It’s something of a core belief about myself as a gamer. But with no one to see my reaction, when I drew the autofail token on a Rotting Remains right before I was going to complete “The Essex County Express”, which killed me just before I was almost certainly going to triumph, I got mad.</p>
<p><em>Arkham Horror</em> is a game where sometimes the random elements really screw you over. You can do a lot to mitigate and prepare for them, but sometimes despite all your best laid plans, the chaos bag spits out the one token that kills you. This is by design. It’s part of how the theme of cosmic horror is expressed in the mechanics. It creates <a href="https://www.lines.com/glossary/sweat/1889">the sweat</a>, a wonderful term I learned from the Nate Silver article linked below.</p>
<p>As I played through the rest of <em>The Dunwich Legacy</em> campaign, I tried to observe these moments of failure, whether mistakes or bad luck, with mindfulness. I endeavored to observe my saltiness without judgment. There were a few more moments throughout the campaign where some bad draws from the encounter deck and the chaos bag brought out the salt, and I watched the salt rise up, then subside and flow away.</p>
<p>Why play a game if it makes you angry or frustrated? That’s a very big question I’m not going to try to answer in a particularly deep way right now, but I’ve found embracing the highs and lows of solo <em>Arkham Horror</em> to be cathartic. And I think <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catharsis">“catharsis”</a> is a useful lens through which to view the experience of negative emotions during play. It was cathartic to get a little salty and for that to be okay. I’m looking forward to starting another solo campaign!</p>
<h2 id="blog-update">Blog update</h2>
<p>As an aside, I’m excited about blogging again. I want to spend more time being curious and thinking about the things that capture my interest, and this seems like a good way to do it. I’m planning to blog more regularly, and also to include links in each post, inspired by the links <a href="https://bastionland.substack.com/">Chris McDowall includes in his newsletter</a>. Maybe I’ll even figure out how RSS feeds work so I can be a real blog boy. (Edit: the ancient mysteries have been revealed. You can now subscribe with a feed reader using the link in the nav bar at the top or bottom.)</p>
<h2 id="sparked-my-curiosity">Sparked my curiosity</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://svenhalvorson.github.io/party_page/portfolio/completely_lost">Sven Halvorson</a> meditates on spending a lot of time on a simple idea that brings him joy</li>
<li><a href="https://www.natesilver.net/p/dont-let-randomness-make-a-fool-of">Nate Silver</a> muses about how when you’ve got 80/20 odds, the 20% side still happens 20% of the time, and that makes people really angry sometimes</li>
<li><a href="https://personabler.blogspot.com/2024/09/a-quick-look-at-big-book-his-majesty.html">Markus - Personable</a> gives a quick look at a big book: His Majesty the Worm</li>
</ul>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>RPG Review: Don't Kill a Bird with a Baseball</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-05-04-dont-kill-a-bird-with-a-baseball.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-05-04-dont-kill-a-bird-with-a-baseball.html</id>
    <published>2024-05-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May  4, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><em>Don’t Kill a Bird with a Baseball: A Randy Johnson TTRPG</em> by JD Clement is a 3-page, 1-shot RPG in which every player plays a parallel version of 6’10” baseball pitcher Randy “the Big Unit” Johnson on March 24, 2001 in the 7 hours leading up to the fateful moment in which he will kill a bird with a baseball. This is a real event, and you can find the video on YouTube (content warning: a bird gets killed by a baseball). The game has simple rules and can be played GM-less, or with a GM.</p>
<p>This review is based on playing in a game of DKABWAB at the <a href="https://goplaynw.org/spring-festival/">2024 Go Play NW Spring Festival</a>. We played with a GM, and I was one of the three Randy Johnsons in the game.</p>
<h2 id="the-premise">The Premise</h2>
<p>The Randy Johnsons you play aren’t our universe’s Randy “the Big Unit” Johnson. Instead, each player is a parallel Randy Johnson, from another reality. Some other kind of unit. And you are all, for similar or different reasons, trying to avoid your fate. Our game included Randy “the Goon Unit” Johnson (with Juggernaut level strength), Randy “the Cursed Unit” Johnson (with the curse to always see the worst possible futures), and Randy “the Acclaimed Unit” Johnson (a sort of cross between an Ent and a Disney princess).</p>
<p>About half way through the session we made contact with each other via a cross-reality conference call, but mostly played out our struggles in parallel. Taking turns in the spotlight meant we got to be audience members watching the other Johnsons when the spotlight wasn’t on us. Shout out to my GM and fellow players for being wonderfully entertaining! Three Johnsons felt like a good number, and I think four would work as well. More than that might get a little unruly in terms of making sure everyone got their turn in the spotlight.</p>
<p>I felt the parallel stories worked particularly well with the theme of all being different versions of the same person. If you preferred, you could easily have your Johnsons find a way to travel through the multi-verse to join forces against fate all together.</p>
<p>The premise of the game is both absurd and specific in a way that made it easy for me to dive into roleplaying my particular Randy Johnson. The writing is evocative and funny and inspired me to delight in piloting the Cursed Unit directly into failure after failure. It was a perfect fit for playing an online game with a bunch of strangers.</p>
<h2 id="the-mechanics">The Mechanics</h2>
<p>The basic resolution mechanic is that you have three stats, and to alter fate, you need to roll under the relevant stat on 2d6. This system is simple, works smoothly, and the fact that the three stats are Baseball, Pitching, and Big makes it even better. I’m a sucker for games with funny stats. You start with two Baseballs, which can be used to reroll a failed roll.</p>
<p>Each time you succeed (or spend a Baseball), you accumulate a resource called Friction, and when you eventually fail a roll, the more Friction you have, the more dire the consequences of your failure. The Friction mechanic was delightful and created a mounting sense of tension after each success.</p>
<p>I haven’t played a game with a mechanic like this before, and I’m excited to see if there are any other games out there exploring an idea like this. I also am definitely going to be thinking about how I can steal this for my own designs! I loved it.</p>
<p>The one piece that I wish the game offered a little more guidance about is how to handle the final moment where you must determine if each Randy Johnson kills a bird with a baseball. The game doesn’t give you any direct guidance about how to run the end of the game. We handled it with a simple roll, just like any other. This worked fine, and meant we didn’t have to stop the momentum and talk about it, but it felt slightly anti-climactic mechanically.</p>
<p>I think I want the “do you kill the bird” moment to either be entirely narrative, or have an extra-special mechanic.</p>
<p>The purely narrative approach would be to resolve it without rolling dice. The GM could of course decide whether or not you’ve succeeded in avoiding your fate, but I think it might be fun to give the decision as to if you kill the bird to the player themselves, and narrate it like an epilogue for your character. You could also give the decision to the other players on the table to pass judgment on each Johnson’s efforts to escape their fate.</p>
<p>If you’re going to resolve it with a roll, I think it would be cool to tie the final roll into the Friction mechanic. For example, instead of rolling under one of your skills, to have to roll under your current Friction score, or under twice your Friction score if you want a higher chance of escaping your fate.</p>
<p>I lean slightly towards the diceless resolution, but it’s hard to know for sure without trying it out. I don’t mind the fact that the game doesn’t tell you exactly how to run this moment, but I think I would have appreciated some suggestions or options.</p>
<h2 id="parting-thoughts">Parting Thoughts</h2>
<p>Overall, I had a blast playing the game, the premise is fantastic, the Friction mechanic is clever, and I’m excited to play it again to see more people come up with more Randy Johnsons and to watch them struggle against destiny.</p>
<p><em>Don’t Kill a Bird with a Baseball: A Randy Johnson TTRPG</em> is written by JD Clement. You can purchase the game from <a href="https://rat-bastard-games.itch.io/dont-kill-a-bird-with-a-baseball">Rat Bastard Games on itch.io</a> for a donation of your choosing. I highly recommend it.</p>
<h1 id="updates-after-gming">Updates after GMing</h1>
<p>I ran <em>Don’t Kill a Bird with a Baseball</em> a few weeks after playing it for the first time, and I wanted to add on a few additional thoughts to the review!</p>
<p>First, running it was just as fun as playing. My three players all brought a ton of energy to their respective Randy Johnsons and we had a blast.</p>
<p>Second, I found the structure of moving through the 7 hours before the incident to be really useful both to manage the overall running time of the game, and to manage the players time in the spotlight. I would advance the hour once everyone had had a chance to do something, and once at least 15-20 minutes had passed. I think our total play time was around 2.5-3 hours (I forget exactly when we shifted from introductions and rules to actually playing). I have a habit of wrapping improv-heavy one-shots pretty quickly (often running 1.5-2 hours), and I’ve been wanting to extend them a little more into the 2-3 hour range, so this landed exactly where I was trying to put it. The structure of the 7 in-game hours really helped me manage the pace!</p>
<p>Third, I tried out my idea of having the other players adjudicate whether each Johnson had successfully altered their fate. When the fateful moment came, I had each player give a quick recap of their successes and failures in altering their fate, had the other two players decide if they had succeeded or failed, then handed narrative control to the Johnson in question to narrate how the final moments played out, epilogue-style. I felt like this worked quite well, and gave the final moment when some birds were killed, and some were not, the weight I felt it deserved.</p>
<p>Finally, the one thing I did somewhat wish I had as a GM is a mechanic for harm or conditions for the characters. If a character breaks a rib, or is high on mushrooms, it’s all narrative, it doesn’t affect the dice. This works fine, but I think I would have enjoyed having the ability to have the characters conditions affect the dice rolls.</p>
<p>I’ve had this same desire when running <a href="http://www.onesevendesign.com/laserfeelings/">Lasers &amp; Feelings</a>, so a few weeks ago I made a (very) quick hack experimenting with adding some rules along those lines: <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/advanced-lasers-feelings">Advanced Lasers &amp; Feelings</a>. I haven’t actually played my hack yet, so this may not actually be a good idea. Gotta play to find out!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Word Wizards and Creative Communities</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-03-31-word-wizards.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2024-03-31-word-wizards.html</id>
    <published>2024-03-31T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-03-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on March 31, 2024
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Since finishing school (which is starting to be a distressingly long time ago), I’ve found it challenging to finish personal art/design projects. Without the structure of school (or of a boss or a client at work), it can be hard to see an idea through the parts where it gets hard. I’ve been curious if one of the things that has been challenging for me is lacking a creative community within which I could work on my projects.</p>
<p>Last year a few friends and I were talking about boardgame and roleplaying game ideas we had rattling around in our heads and we decided to start meeting up weekly to work on our projects, helping each other playtest, and sharing our progress. This turned out to be hugely helpful for me, and I recently finished my first game! It’s a rules-light RPG about wizards.</p>
<p>Check it out here: <a href="https://brendanalbano.itch.io/word-wizards">Download Word Wizards</a></p>
<p>And a quick shout out to Dodge Greenley, who did the fabulous art. You should hire him for all your illustration/storyboard/writing/funny-cartoon-stuff needs!</p>
<p>I’m thrilled to have finished a project like this and am excited to get to the next one. Even though it was a solo project that I could have done alone, I suspect that if I had gone it alone I wouldn’t have done it! Continuing to build my creative community will be a key part of bringing all the ideas buzzing around in my head to life!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Roll for Shoes in the Dark</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-06-15-roll-for-shoes-in-the-dark.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-06-15-roll-for-shoes-in-the-dark.html</id>
    <published>2023-06-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on June 15, 2023
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Worlds Beyond Number is doing a 2-shot using the RPG Roll for Shoes which sounds like a really charming rules-light system. I’ve been having a lot of fun with extremely minimal RPGs like Lasers and Feelings and Electric Bastionland recently, and Roll for Shoes sounds right up my alley.</p>
<p>I’ve also been wanting to dip my toes in doing a little RPG design by hacking one of these rules light systems. So here is a simple idea for a Roll for Shoes hack:</p>
<h2 id="roll-for-shoes-in-the-dark">Roll for Shoes in the Dark</h2>
<ul>
<li>Use step 1 of <a href="https://rollforshoes.com/">Roll for Shoes</a> to assemble your dice pool</li>
<li>In step 2, resolve the dice pool per <a href="https://bladesinthedark.com/core-system">Blades in the Dark</a>’s dice pool resolution system: roll the dice, read the single highest die, 6 is a full success, 4-5 is partial success or success with complication, 1-3 is failure.</li>
<li>All other rules per Roll for Shoes</li>
</ul>
<p>My thinking is two-fold. First, partial successes are fun. Second, because it doesn’t require doing any arithmetic, and doesn’t require the GM to set a difficulty for the opposed roll, it gets you right back to the action. Does Roll for Shoes benefit from these changes? No idea! I need to actually try playing this to find out. But it sounds fun on paper!</p>
<p>Edit: apparently I am not the first person to come up with this idea! I guess that shouldn’t be too surprising. Here is someone who beat me to it: <a href="https://boocherry.itch.io/shoes-in-the-dark">https://boocherry.itch.io/shoes-in-the-dark</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Reading List 2023 Q1</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-04-01-reading-list-2023-q1.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-04-01-reading-list-2023-q1.html</id>
    <published>2023-04-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on April  1, 2023
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I had so much fun with my reading goal last year, I’m running it back. Rather than wait until the end, I figured I’d do periodic updates along the way. I’m being as flexible as I feel inclined to be any given month about what counts as a book. Below are the books I read in the first three months of 2023.</p>
<p>(Link to last year’s <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com2023-01-02-2022-reading-list.html">reading goal</a> post because my blog template gets weird if I put a link in the first paragraph and I haven’t gotten around to fixing it).</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Stories of Your Life and Others</em> by Ted Chiang</li>
<li><em>Legends and Lattes</em> by Travis Baldree</li>
<li><em>The Raven Tower</em> by Ann Leckie</li>
<li><em>When the Tiger Came Down the Mountain</em> by Nghi Vo</li>
<li><em>Binti</em> by Nnedi Okorafor</li>
<li><em>Binti: Home</em> by Nnedi Okorafor</li>
<li><em>Binti: The Night Masquerade</em> by Nnedi Okorafor</li>
<li><em>Into the Riverlands</em> by Nghi Vo</li>
<li><em>Starstruck</em> by Elaine Lee and Michael Kaluta</li>
<li><em>Blades in the Dark</em> by John Harper</li>
<li><em>Mork Bork</em> by Pelle Nilsson and Johan Nohr</li>
<li><em>Four Thousand Weeks</em> by Oliver Burkeman</li>
<li><em>Saga Vol. 1</em> by Brian K. Vaughan and Fiona Staples</li>
<li><em>Starstruck: Old Proldiers Never Die</em> by Elaine Lee and Michael Kaluta</li>
<li><em>Banana</em> by Dan Koeppel</li>
<li><em>The Hundred Thousand Kingdoms</em> by N. K. Jemisin</li>
</ul>
<p>I decided I wanted to read more comics this year, and kicking things off with <em>Starstruck</em> was a delight. It was a little hard to follow at times, but once I got my sea legs (space legs?), I was in love. The universe of <em>Starstruck</em> is equal parts whimsical and cynical in a truly joyous way. The comics are available online at <a href="https://starstruckcomics.com/">https://starstruckcomics.com/</a>, but I thought reading it on paper was well worth it.</p>
<p>If you’re into the particularly nerdy depths that is RPG actual plays, I got turned onto <em>Starstruck</em> by the <a href="https://www.dropout.tv/dimension-20/season:13">Dimension 20 Actual Play</a>. Speaking of actual plays, I am adoring <a href="https://worldsbeyondnumber.com/">Worlds Beyond Number</a>. The Children’s Campaign available on the Worlds Beyond Number Patreon is well worth it.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Sourdough Loaf Update</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-03-07-sourdough-loaf-update.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-03-07-sourdough-loaf-update.html</id>
    <published>2023-03-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on March  7, 2023
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>A quick loaf update!</p>
<p>I’ve baked a few more loaves since <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com2023-02-19-the-long-loaf.html">my post</a> about Andrew Barton’s <em>The Long Loaf</em>, and in that time my sourdough starter has grown more vigorous and now fully fills my loaf pan, so if I bake it with the lid on, I get a strange and charming square loaf like a pain de mie or pullman loaf.</p>
<figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2023-03-07-sourdough-loaf-update/square-loaf.jpg" alt="Loaf" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Loaf</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The loaf shown above had two changes to the recipe in my previous post:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I left the lid on the whole time in the oven, rather than taking it off for the second half of the bake.</li>
<li>I forgot about my bread several times during the process of making the dough, so all my timing was abnormal, and due to the magic of Barton’s loaf pan approach, it all worked out just fine anyways!</li>
</ol>
<p>One of these two changes gave the interior of the loaf an even more pudding-like consistency, which I quite liked! Next I will leave the lid on the whole time again, and also bake the bread at a single temperature for the full baking time, rather than 500F for the first half and 450F for the second half like I have been.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Long Loaf review</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-02-19-the-long-loaf.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-02-19-the-long-loaf.html</id>
    <published>2023-02-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on February 19, 2023
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I’ve made a bunch of loaves from <em>Flour, Water, Salt, Yeast</em> by Ken Forkish, but they always felt like a special occasion. Which is delightful. I love special occasions. But, what about that romantic idea of being a person who bakes bread regularly as a normal and charming part of your weekly routine? That’s where <a href="https://www.twoplumpress.com/bookshop/the-long-loaf-bread-for-all-days-by-andrew-barton"><em>The Long Loaf</em> by Andrew Barton</a> comes in.</p>
<p><em>The Long Loaf</em> is a blend of essays, stories, recipes all devoted to the romance of bread. And in particular, to the romance of bread baked in a loaf pan. <em>The Long Loaf</em> gave me permission to play with the recipes. Skip steps. Add steps. Make a process that works for me. Below is my weekly bread ritual. It’s pretty similar to the one in Barton’s book, but with a few bits of process I liked from Forkish’s, and the timing that works for my schedule, preferences, and somewhat cold kitchen.</p>
<p>In addition to the recipe and schedule below, if you’ve never made sourdough bread before, you would be well served by getting one of the above books, or watching some youtube videos to get a feel for the techniques used to mix, fold and handle the dough.</p>
<h2 id="recipe">Recipe</h2>
<p>Weighing your ingredients is great. Baker’s percentages in parentheses. If you aren’t familiar with baker’s percentages, you can ignore them, <a href="https://www.kingarthurbaking.com/pro/reference/bakers-percentage">but here’s a quick explanation</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>300g all-purpose flour (60%)</li>
<li>150g whole-wheat flour (30%)</li>
<li>50g rye flour (10%)</li>
<li>450g water at 95F (90%)</li>
<li>13g salt (2.6%)</li>
<li>115g mature sourdough starter (I mix my starter with the same baker’s percentages as the loaf so that I don’t have to do any math when adding it in).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="day-1---morning-feed-the-starter">Day 1 - Morning: Feed the starter</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Take your starter out of your fridge (both books have good instructions for how to make a sourdough starter). I store my starter in a glass Weck jar. I use the rubber seal and the glass lid, but I don’t use the little clips. I have no evidence that it matters, but this feels right to me.</li>
<li>Discard all but a few tablespoons of starter. I save my discard in the fridge and occasionally make it into pancakes or other quick breads.</li>
<li>Add 100g of flour to your starter jar. I like to use the same flour ratio I use in my loaf, so that comes out to 60g all-purpose flour, 30g whole wheat flout, 10g rye flour.</li>
<li>Add 90g of 95F water to the jar. Mix well and leave covered on the counter until the following morning. Whatever you use as a lid, make sure that gases can still escape.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="day-2---morning-mix-the-dough">Day 2 - Morning: Mix the dough</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Mix and fold the flour and water with your hands in a large bowl or tub. I like the mixing techniques in <em>Flour, Water, Salt Yeast</em>. Let the mixture autolyse for 30 minutes.</li>
<li>Add the starter and the salt and again, mix and fold the mixture.</li>
<li>Discard any extra starter so that only a few tablespoons remain in the jar. Feed the starter with the same ratio of flour and water as the previous morning. I like to leave it out on the counter for an hour before returning it to the fridge, but that may be mostly superstition and it can be returned to the fridge right away.</li>
<li>Over the next 5 or so hours of bulk fermentation, fold the mixture at least three times.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="day-2---afternoon-into-the-pan">Day 2 - Afternoon: Into the pan</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Butter or oil your loaf pan. <em>The Long Loaf</em> bakes a dough with 1000g of flour in a charmingly large pan, but that’s more bread than I eat in a week, so I use a smaller 9” x 4” Pullman loaf pan. I like the square sides and built in lid of the Pullman pan.</li>
<li>Transfer the dough into the loaf pan. Cover and refrigerate overnight.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="day-3---morning-bake">Day 3 - Morning: Bake</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Preheat the oven to 500F and set the load pan out on the counter to warm up. Make sure to grease the lid of the loaf pan. I’ve never been very good at interpreting the finger poke test, but you can try your hand at poking the dough to see if it’s properly proofed. I usually don’t bother and trust the wonderful flexibility of the loaf pan method.</li>
<li>Put the pan in the oven with the lid on and bake for 25-30 minutes. In my pan, the loaf will rise up and press gently against the lid, but doesn’t turn into a full square like some Pullman loafs.</li>
<li>Remove the lid, turn the over down to 450F, and bake for another 25-30 minutes.</li>
<li>Remove the loaf from the pan and cool completely on a wire rack before cutting. Once it is culled, I store the loaf in the Pullman pan, thanks to the integrated lid!</li>
</ol>
<p>That’s a lot of steps all typed out, but the flexibility of this approach has allowed it to become a lovely weekly ritual for me, and I’ve got <em>The Long Loaf</em> to thank for that!</p>
<figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2023-02-19-the-long-loaf/loaf.jpg" alt="Loaf" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Loaf</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2023-02-19-the-long-loaf/loaf-crumb.jpg" alt="Loaf and Crumb" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Loaf and Crumb</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Edit: here is <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com2023-03-07-sourdough-loaf-update.html">a brief loaf update</a> as my starter has continued to evolve!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Boy Problems RPG Review</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-01-21-boy-problems-rpg-review.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-01-21-boy-problems-rpg-review.html</id>
    <published>2023-01-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on January 21, 2023
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I’ve played Dungeons &amp; Dragons on and off since I was a kid. I’ve played some other role-playing games here and there as well, but D&amp;D has always occupied the lion’s share of RPGs I’ve played. The on and off was mostly on when I was a kid. And mostly off for the next 10-15 years. Lately I’ve been getting back into the hobby, which has been a delight. One of the things I’ve been enjoying is branching out and trying other RPGs.</p>
<p>Lasers and Feelings is a one-page rpg for playing a game in the genre of Star Trek. <a href="http://onesevendesign.com/lasers_and_feelings_rpg.pdf">Give it a quick read. It’s only one page!</a> The rest of my thoughts will make more sense if you’ve familiarized yourself with Lasers and Feelings. I’m also assuming you’ve played D&amp;D before!</p>
<p><a href="https://boyproblems.ca/boyproblems">Boy Problems</a> uses the same basic rules as Lasers and Feelings, but trades Star Trek for cyberpunk + Carly Rae Jepson.</p>
<p>A few months ago, I GMed a session of Boy Problems and it was exciting to play a game that was so different than D&amp;D. I ran the scenario that comes with boy problems, which is a heist taking place during a gala at MoMA NY in the near future.</p>
<p>A few things that stuck with me after the game:</p>
<p>The speedy resolution mechanic made it really easy to split the party and have a hacker character trying to get into the IT room, while another character got hired to cater the gala, and another snuck in as a performer. Cutting back and forth between the action allowed a cinematic feel that felt like a heist movie. I’ve never felt comfortable splitting the party in 3 or 4 different places like that in a D&amp;D type system. Not that it can’t be done in D&amp;D, but it felt like this system really supported it, and that felt really appropriate for the genre.</p>
<p>The second thing was that using the same resolution mechanic for everything made it easy to expand and contract time. Sometimes you could make a single role to determine if you seduced the security guard (and then fade to black, first time using safety tools as well and a “pause, fast forward” was executed excellently in that moment). Other times when two people are diving for a fumbled taser during a fight you could make a roll for each leap, each grab, each time the taser gets fumbled and you need to decide where it bounces. It felt like I could drop into slow motion, which was really fun!</p>
<p>The last thing I noticed, was that it was exhausting. I realized that as a GM, D&amp;D type combat allows me to take a breather from improv storytelling. Without a crunchy combat subsystem, it was all improv all the time!</p>
<p>There are a lot of things I enjoy about D&amp;D and similar games, but playing a game that took a very different approach has enhanced my RPG experience tremendously. If you’re an RPG player that mostly only plays one game system, whether it’s D&amp;D or something else, try taking a detour into something completely different every now and then!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2022 Reading List</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-01-02-2022-reading-list.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2023-01-02-2022-reading-list.html</id>
    <published>2023-01-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on January  2, 2023
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>As part of a larger effort to spend less time on my phone and more time doing things I love, I read 61 books in 2022. <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com2020-10-14-when-did-i-stop-reading.html">I wrote about</a> how it was strange that I didn’t read very much despite very much identifying as a reader back in 2020. After a solid warmup year in 2021, I really hit my stride in 2022.</p>
<p>As with a lot of things, I was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gRBkIdc_VYU">inspired by Cal Newport</a>. I started off the year with a more modest goal of 2 books a month, then, after an 11 book bender in May, I figured I could handle a 5 books a month goal. Since I had some uneven months already, I decided to go for an average of 5 books a month, rather than exactly 5 every month. This goal felt aggressive, but flexible, and it kept me motivated through the year.</p>
<p>Shifting from reading a little to reading a lot, and spending less time on my phone as a result, was a huge boon to my mental health and happiness this year.</p>
<p>Without further ado, here are the 61 books I read in 2022. My favorites are noted “fav”. This table may break the layout on my blog. If it does, apologies. I’m working on it :)</p>
<p>If the table below is illegible, try <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1nAklTe0NmjYa_hfbM6MjcpifWdPGfuhFnIthQqbKRyw/edit?usp=sharing">this version on google drive</a></p>
<table style="width:100%;">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 5%" />
<col style="width: 7%" />
<col style="width: 32%" />
<col style="width: 21%" />
<col style="width: 25%" />
<col style="width: 7%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Number</th>
<th>Month</th>
<th>Title</th>
<th>Series</th>
<th>Author</th>
<th>Favorites</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>January</td>
<td>Deep Work</td>
<td></td>
<td>Cal Newport</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>January</td>
<td>The Graveyard Book</td>
<td></td>
<td>Neil Gaiman</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>January</td>
<td>The Curse of Chalion</td>
<td>World of the Five Gods 1</td>
<td>Lois McMaster Bujold</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>January</td>
<td>Paladin of Souls</td>
<td>World of the Five Gods 2</td>
<td>Lois McMaster Bujold</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>February</td>
<td>Piranesi</td>
<td></td>
<td>Susanna Clarke</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>February</td>
<td>New Suns</td>
<td></td>
<td>ed. Nisi Shawl</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>March</td>
<td>Designing Design</td>
<td></td>
<td>Kenya Hara</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>March</td>
<td>Precision Nutrition</td>
<td></td>
<td>John Berardi</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>April</td>
<td>Delicious</td>
<td></td>
<td>Rob Dunn, Monica Sanchez</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>April</td>
<td>This is How You Lose the Time War</td>
<td></td>
<td>Amal El-Mohtar, Max Gladstone</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>April</td>
<td>Among Others</td>
<td></td>
<td>Jo Walton</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>April</td>
<td>A Psalm for the Wild-built</td>
<td>Monk &amp; Robot 1</td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Travel Light</td>
<td></td>
<td>Naomi Mitchison</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>The Long Way to a Small Angry Planet</td>
<td>Wayfarers 1</td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Closed and Common Orbit</td>
<td>Wayfarers 2</td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Record of a Spaceborn Few</td>
<td>Wayfarers 3</td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>A The Galaxy and the Ground Within</td>
<td>Wayfarers 4</td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Bird by Bird</td>
<td></td>
<td>Anne Lamott</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Nova</td>
<td></td>
<td>Samuel R. Delany</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>The Caves of Steel</td>
<td></td>
<td>Isaac Asimov</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Foundation</td>
<td>Foundation</td>
<td>Isaac Asimov</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>Tell the Machine Goodnight</td>
<td></td>
<td>Katie Williams</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td>May</td>
<td>How Long ‘Til Black Future Month</td>
<td></td>
<td>N.K. Jemisin</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td>June</td>
<td>Gold Fame Citrus</td>
<td></td>
<td>Claire Vaye Watkins</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td>June</td>
<td>Skyward Inn</td>
<td></td>
<td>Aliya Whiteley</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>26</td>
<td>June</td>
<td>Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep</td>
<td></td>
<td>Philip K. Dick</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>27</td>
<td>June</td>
<td>On Bullshit</td>
<td></td>
<td>Harry G. Frankfurt</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td>June</td>
<td>5/3/1</td>
<td></td>
<td>Jim Wendler</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>29</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>The Dispossessed</td>
<td></td>
<td>Ursula K. Le Guin</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>Three Parts Dead</td>
<td>The Craft Sequence 1</td>
<td>Max Gladstone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>There is No Good Card for This</td>
<td></td>
<td>Emily McDowell, Kelsey Crowe</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>32</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>The Art of Lifting</td>
<td></td>
<td>Greg Nuckols</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>33</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>The Science of Lifting</td>
<td></td>
<td>Greg Nuckols</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>34</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>Several People are Typing</td>
<td></td>
<td>Calvin Kasulke</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>The Shards of Earth</td>
<td>The Final Architecture 1</td>
<td>Adrian Tchaikovsky</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>36</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>Leviathan Wakes</td>
<td>The Expanse 1</td>
<td>James S.A. Corey</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>37</td>
<td>July</td>
<td>A Prayer for the Crown-shy</td>
<td>Monk &amp; Robot 2</td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>38</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>Klara and the Sun</td>
<td></td>
<td>Kazuo Ishiguro</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>39</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>At Home</td>
<td></td>
<td>Bill Bryson</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>Caliban’s War</td>
<td>The Expanse 2</td>
<td>James S.A. Corey</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>41</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>Two Serpents Rise</td>
<td>The Craft Sequence 2</td>
<td>Max Gladstone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>42</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>Full Fathom Five</td>
<td>The Craft Sequence 3</td>
<td>Max Gladstone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>43</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>Last First Snow</td>
<td>The Craft Sequence 4</td>
<td>Max Gladstone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>44</td>
<td>August</td>
<td>Four Roads Cross</td>
<td>The Craft Sequence 5</td>
<td>Max Gladstone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45</td>
<td>September</td>
<td>The Ruin of Angels</td>
<td>The Craft Sequence 6</td>
<td>Max Gladstone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>46</td>
<td>September</td>
<td>Abaddon’s Gate</td>
<td>The Expanse 3</td>
<td>James S.A. Corey</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>47</td>
<td>September</td>
<td>Nona the Ninth</td>
<td>The Locked Tomb</td>
<td>Tamsyn Muir</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>48</td>
<td>October</td>
<td>Play Unsafe</td>
<td></td>
<td>Graham Walmsley</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>49</td>
<td>October</td>
<td>Never Have I Ever</td>
<td></td>
<td>Isabel Yap</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50</td>
<td>October</td>
<td>Return of the Lazy Dungeon Master</td>
<td></td>
<td>Michael E. Shea</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>51</td>
<td>October</td>
<td>Swordspoint</td>
<td>The Riverside Series 1</td>
<td>Ellen Kushner</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>52</td>
<td>November</td>
<td>The Eyes of the Void</td>
<td>The Final Architecture 2</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>53</td>
<td>November</td>
<td>Cibola Burn</td>
<td>The Expanse 4</td>
<td>James S.A. Corey</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>54</td>
<td>November</td>
<td>Nemisis Games</td>
<td>The Expanse 5</td>
<td>James S.A. Corey</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>55</td>
<td>November</td>
<td>The Stars are Legion</td>
<td>Wayward Children 1</td>
<td>Kameron Hurley</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>56</td>
<td>December</td>
<td>Noor</td>
<td></td>
<td>Nnedi Okorafor</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>57</td>
<td>December</td>
<td>Floralinda and the Forty Flight Tower</td>
<td></td>
<td>Tamsyn Muir</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>58</td>
<td>December</td>
<td>The Empress of Salt and Fortune</td>
<td>The Singing Hills Cycle 1</td>
<td>Nghi Vo</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>59</td>
<td>December</td>
<td>Every Heart a Doorway</td>
<td></td>
<td>Seanan McGuire</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>60</td>
<td>December</td>
<td>To Be Taught If Fortunate</td>
<td></td>
<td>Becky Chambers</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>61</td>
<td>December</td>
<td>The Long Loaf</td>
<td></td>
<td>Andrew Barton</td>
<td>Fav</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Zen of Python for Architects</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2022-08-21-the-zen-of-python-for-architects.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2022-08-21-the-zen-of-python-for-architects.html</id>
    <published>2022-08-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-08-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on August 21, 2022
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>I wouldn’t be surprised if Christopher Alexander’s “A Pattern Language” was more influential in the field of computer programming than it was in architecture. I’ve encountered the discussion of patterns much more frequently in books about computer programming than in books about architecture, and I’ve read a lot more architecture books than programming books. The computer programming books have given me a lot more to think about. There’s a poetry and a humor to writing about programming that I miss in architecture. Take <a href="https://peps.python.org/pep-0020/">The Zen of Python</a>, a set of style guidelines for the programming language Python:</p>
<ul>
<li>Beautiful is better than ugly.</li>
<li>Explicit is better than implicit.</li>
<li>Simple is better than complex.</li>
<li>Complex is better than complicated.</li>
<li>Flat is better than nested.</li>
<li>Sparse is better than dense.</li>
<li>Readability counts.</li>
<li>Special cases aren’t special enough to break the rules.</li>
<li>Although practicality beats purity.</li>
<li>Errors should never pass silently.</li>
<li>Unless explicitly silenced.</li>
<li>In the face of ambiguity, refuse the temptation to guess.</li>
<li>There should be one– and preferably only one –obvious way to do it.</li>
<li>Although that way may not be obvious at first unless you’re Dutch.</li>
<li>Now is better than never.</li>
<li>Although never is often better than <em>right</em> now.</li>
<li>If the implementation is hard to explain, it’s a bad idea.</li>
<li>If the implementation is easy to explain, it may be a good idea.</li>
<li>Namespaces are one honking great idea – let’s do more of those!</li>
</ul>
<p>This is hot shit. I think the design ethos is clear even if you don’t have a programming background. There is humor and paradox. It’s opinionated. It’s irreverent and serious. I love it. I’ve tried to write a Zen of Python inspired style guide for my designs a few times. I haven’t gotten a full set that sings yet, but it’s rewarding every time I try. Here are a few Kate and I came up with while working on the design for a sauna we’re planning on building in our back yard:</p>
<ul>
<li>Out-of-time is more romantic than timeless.</li>
<li>It should make sense to build.</li>
<li>Wonder and delight should be a part of our everyday lives.</li>
<li>But we shouldn’t forget what planet we’re on.</li>
<li>Design should be generous.</li>
<li>Using less concrete is better – unless it’s not.</li>
</ul>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Coffee Shop Thoughts: Part 1 - Introduction and Sawada</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2022-08-14-coffee-shop-thoughts-part-1.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2022-08-14-coffee-shop-thoughts-part-1.html</id>
    <published>2022-08-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-08-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on August 14, 2022
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>When I step into a coffee shop that gets everything right, I step into a subtle alternate reality where I am cooler and more creative, less anxious, more thoughtful. The best coffee shops are remarkably reliable in achieving this effect. What is it about these coffee shops that transports me? What comes from the space itself, the coffee, the food, the staff, the other patrons, what comes from me?</p>
<p>The entrance to Sawada Coffee in Chicago feels like a secret. It’s not. It says “Sawada Coffee” right on the door. But the faded paint of the logo blends into the surrounding graffiti and wheatpastes on the old brick building. The half-face half-skull portrait of owner Hiroshi Sawada is undeniably cool. When I open the door I feel like I’m I’m entering an exclusive club. But I feel like a member. (At least, I assume that is what it feels like. I’ve never been a member at an exclusive club.) The needle that a coffee shop like Sawada threads is that instead of making me feel like I’m not cool enough, it makes me feel cooler.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Through the door and around a corner and Sawada opens up. It’s in a large warehouse space that also contains the excellent Green Street Smoked Meats. The atmosphere is moody and warm. The ceilings are tall and dark. The Sawada portion of the warehouse is raised a half-dozen steps and contains a large central table for communal seating, the bar, and a row of seating along the window. There are skateboards on the walls and a Supreme punching bag. There is stadium seating transitioning down to the lower area containing the many wood tables and benches of Green Street Meats.</p>
<p>Sawada specializes in espresso and matcha drinks, and serves doughnuts from the Doughnut Vault. Their signature drink is the military latte: a matcha latte with cocoa powder, vanilla syrup and a shot of espresso. It’s sounds way overdone. It isn’t. It’s perfect. At least, it’s perfect for me, just like the entry, the atmosphere, the way I can pick through the many seating options and find myself just the right corner that fits my mood. I feel at peace. I feel happy.</p>
<p>In future posts I will dig into the mechanisms that I think create this effect and explore more of my favorite coffee shops to look for common themes. One of the biggest and broadest mechanisms is the all-encompassing vision. Every part of Sawada supports the experience. When I step into Sawada, I feel like I am stepping into an entire world that Hiroshi Sawada has created. Everything is as it should be.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Thanksgiving on the Lost Coast</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2021-11-28-thanksgiving-on-the-lost-coast.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2021-11-28-thanksgiving-on-the-lost-coast.html</id>
    <published>2021-11-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on November 28, 2021
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Kate and I took the week of Thanksgiving off work and ran away to northern California for a much needed vacation. We visited the redwoods and the Lost Coast and enjoyed some miraculously good weather. The redwoods were peaceful and the Lost Coast was gorgeous and felt really unique. Well worth a visit!</p>
<p>First off, here are <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/AxJ6kLMi9nJyPxo67">the photos!</a></p>
<p>Read on for the blow-by-blow.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="day-1-nov.-23-portland-to-the-redwoods">Day 1, Nov. 23: Portland to the Redwoods</h2>
<ul>
<li>Driving: Portland, OR to Prairie Creek Redwoods State Park, via I-5 -&gt; 199 -&gt; 101.</li>
<li>Camp: Elk Creek Campground, Prairie Creek Redwoods State Park</li>
</ul>
<p>The sun came out as soon as we left Portland which felt like a good omen. The drive along 199 and 101 was gorgeous curving highway and big trees. Stopped at Cristina’s Mexican Restaurant in Crescent City which was everything you hope for in a hole-in-the-wall restaurant in a small town. High energy place where they knew everyone else’s usual order by heart. Kate said, “just water for me, but you’re getting a horchata right?” They knew what was up and brought us two horchatas anyways.</p>
<p>Elk Creek Campground was fully booked, so it was definitely good we reserved ahead of time. The campground had a pretty quiet vibe despite being full. I bet it gets loud in the summer though. As promised, we saw several elk as we arrived. It was cold and wet, and we had breakfast sandwiches for dinner (egg, bacon, cheese, English muffin). We slept in the car, which is slightly too small for both of us (mainly because I like to thrash around a lot at night), but also very convenient and very warm.</p>
<h2 id="day-2-nov.-24-redwoods-to-the-lost-coast">Day 2, Nov. 24: Redwoods to the Lost Coast</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hike: Prairie Creek Redwoods SP - Big Tree -&gt; Foothill Trail -&gt; South Fork Trail -&gt; Rhododendron Trail -&gt; Cathedral Trees Trail</li>
<li>Drive: Prairie Creek Redwoods SP to Mattole Campground vis 101 -&gt; 211 -&gt; Mattole Rd -&gt; Lighthouse Rd</li>
<li>Camp: Mattole Campground, King Range National Conservation Area (Lost Coast)</li>
</ul>
<p>Started the day off visiting the Big Tree (which is indeed a big tree), then hiking a loop in the redwoods. The big trees are magical and nice to touch. A particular highlight was a burned out tree on the Rhododendron Trail with a gorgeous charcoal interior that you could walk through. If you looked up it had an oculus at the top letting in beams of light that highlighted the charcoal. I’ve always wanted to visit Peter Zumthor’s Bruder Klaus Field Chapel, and I think this tree might have satisfied that desire for me.</p>
<p>Next we drove down to the Lost Coast, through the charming town of Ferndale, which we knew we definitely wanted to stop at on the way back. The drive into the Lost Coast was amazing and reminded me of driving in Iceland, except with cows instead of sheep. This drive was another trip highlight. I didn’t use to be a big driving person, but I’m slowly becoming more appreciative of scenic drives. Kate had to stop me from getting out of the car to try and pet the cows. They had their winter coats and looked exceptionally soft.</p>
<p>Mattole campground is a first-come-first-serve BLM campground that supposedly never totally fills up, despite only having 15 sites. It was 2/3 full when we arrived. It’s a cute but windy campground and seems like a great base to explore the north half of the Lost Coast. Notably, it doesn’t have water, so make sure to fill up before you arrive! Once you’re hiking, there are lots of streams in the Lost Coast area where you can filter water, but you’ll probably want to bring in water for camp.</p>
<p>We had Annie’s Mac and Cheese for dinner and slept in our new luxurious 4-person car camping tent. We were glad we brought earplugs, because the wind flapping the tent walls was extremely loud. We’re still experimenting with car camping setup, since we do more backpacking than car camping, we don’t exactly know what we like yet. Sleeping in the car is pretty great, except that our 2005 Subaru Forester is just slightly too small to be super comfortable. I think in general I prefer the big car camping tent unless the weather is truly horrendous and the solid walls of the car are worth being a little cramped. On a solo trip, sleeping in the car would be easy and I’d probably go for it every time. Maybe one day we’ll be blessed with a cute 4WD imported Japanese van.</p>
<p>Disaster struck when I woke up in the middle of the night with the hiccups and they lasted for at least an hour, which was bizarre and kind of miserable. I read an ebook on my phone until they went away and was eventually able to go back to sleep. Disaster averted.</p>
<h2 id="day-3-nov.-25-thanksgiving-on-the-lost-coast">Day 3, Nov. 25: Thanksgiving on the Lost Coast</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hike: <a href="https://caltopo.com/m/PSRPS">Lost Coast - Mattole Campground -&gt; Punta Gorda Lighthouse</a></li>
<li>Camp: Mattole Campground, King Range National Conservation Area (Lost Coast)</li>
</ul>
<p>Several sections of the Lost Coast Trail are impassible at high tide, included one section between the campground and the lighthouse we wanted to check out. The tide tables were not in our favor, unless we wanted to hike in the dark, but luckily there was a trail that went up into the bluffs that avoided the impassible section. The detour turned out to be a worthwhile hike regardless of the tides. Great views and a nice change of pace from walking on the beach.</p>
<p>Punta Gorda Lighthouse was incredibly charming, and the ladder up to the top looks like it’s been maintained to some extent to make it easy to climb up and check it out. The lighthouse was delightful, both practical and whimsical. The main building was about 10’ x 20’ with three rooms and a symmetrical plan: entry room, circular ladder room, kitchen/workbench room. The leftover spaces formed by putting a circular room into a rectangular building created 4 closets. Up the ladder is the lighthouse platform where presumably the lamp use to be. A smaller building a few steps down the path appeared to be for storing fuel.</p>
<p>I love this little lighthouse. So much of my architectural thoughts are spent on figuring out what our clients like, and I sometimes feel a little lost when I think about what I like. Exploring the Punta Gorda Lighthouse was grounding and rejuvenating.</p>
<p>On the beach were two large groups of elephant seals sleeping and flopping around. We had a snack and hung out at the lighthouse and watched the seals for a while before eventually heading back to camp.</p>
<p>Our Thanksgiving dinner consisted of instant mashed potatoes, gravy, stovetop stuffing, canned cranberry sauce and bacon. It was great. Stuffing might make it into the camping food rotation more often! It’s very satisfying on a cold windy evening. We even had leftovers for lunch the next day, which seemed like an important part of a Thanksgiving dinner.</p>
<h2 id="day-4-nov.-26-back-to-the-redwoods">Day 4, Nov. 26: Back to the Redwoods</h2>
<ul>
<li>Drive: Mattole Campground to Prairie Creek Redwoods SP via Lighthouse Rd -&gt; Mattole Rd -&gt; 211 -&gt; 101</li>
<li>Road Trip Stop: Ferndale, CA</li>
<li>Hike: Prairie Creek Redwoods SP - Fern Canyon, Prairie Creek Trail -&gt; Nature Trail</li>
<li>Camp: Elk Creek Campground, Prairie Creek Redwoods SP</li>
</ul>
<p>The drive out of the Lost Coast was just as lovely as the drive in. Didn’t seem like much was open in Petrolia the day after Thanksgiving, so we headed on to Ferndale where we parked the car to explore. Ferndale has a remarkable collection of historic Victorian homes and shops and a charming touristy/artsy vibe.</p>
<p>We got a coffee at Mind’s Eye Manufactory and Coffee Lounge, which would have been cute enough if it was just as a coffee shop, but it’s attached to a wood shop where local artists rent bench space and you can take a class to learn to make a traditional skin-on-frame sea kayak. The wood shop and the coffee shop are owned by the same couple. Truly a dream setup, and maybe a pretty serious model for Kate and my future someday! I could imagine running a coffee shop as the storefront to a design studio.</p>
<p>Continuing on the road trip theme of the day, we did the short Fern Canyon loop at Prairie Creek Redwoods. Despite the seasonal bridges being removed, it was a zoo! Lots of families with kids having a blast climbing around and getting wet and adults trying to carefully pick their way through balancing on logs and rocks.</p>
<p>We headed back at Elk Prairie Campground and did a short walk on the Prairie Creek Trail and Nature Trail, which ended with Kate getting her feet wet and me balancing on a somewhat slippy log, as the seasonal bridge had been removed from a stream crossing at the very end of the loop. Our final camp dinner of the trip was Knorr instant Spanish rice, Santa Fe instant refried beans, salsa, avocado, cheddar cheese, and corn chips. We call it the Fancy Skurka. (The traditional Skurka is instant rice, instant beans, cheese and Fritos, and is a backpacking staple). It is a close cousin to Frito Pie.</p>
<h2 id="day-5-nov.-27-back-to-portland">Day 5, Nov. 27: Back to Portland</h2>
<ul>
<li>Drive: Prairie Creek Redwoods State Park SP to Portland, OR via 101 -&gt; 199 -&gt; I-5.</li>
<li>Road Trip Stops: Gasquet Market, Gasquet, CA; It’s a Burl, Kerby, OR; K&amp;R Drive Inn, Oakland, OR</li>
</ul>
<p>On the way home we bought a box of amazing Alfajor sandwich cookies in Gasquet, visited “It’s a Burl” in Kerby (just go look at the photos), and finished the trip with a burger at the K&amp;R Drive Inn, which has a very cute sign.</p>
<p>Along the way we did a lot of thinking and talking while we are a little out of practice at taking vacations, I feel more well rested than I have in quite a while.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Bad Internet</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2021-08-29-the-bad-internet.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2021-08-29-the-bad-internet.html</id>
    <published>2021-08-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on August 29, 2021
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>“Are you on the good internet or the bad internet?” Kate asks.</p>
<p>The good internet is a fun frivolous diversion. The bad internet makes me sad.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>I still find myself typing “www.facebook.com” into my browser by muscle memory, despite the fact that I deleted my Facebook months ago, and haven’t really used Facebook for several years. The process of managing my addictive behaviors related to social media, web browsing, and my cellphone has been long and slow. The ludic loop of checking and refreshing Instagram, YouTube, discord, news, email, etc to see if new content has appeared in my media slot machine is nearly irresistible to me. After a session at the bad internet casino, I leave a little sadder than when I arrived.</p>
<p>The good internet involves intentionally consuming a piece of media. The bad internet involves groping desperately for media to consume. The good internet might be watching a new board game review on Shut Up and Sit Down’s YouTube channel. The bad internet is scrolling through the endless list of videos the algorithm serves to me, occasionally watching the auto play preview for a minute or two, before scrolling onward.</p>
<p>For the last several years, I’ve been making a focused effort to spend less time on the bad internet and more time on the good internet. It hasn’t been particularly successful.</p>
<p>Kate and I recently got a puppy, which has given me a lot of perspective on undesirable behaviors. If your dog has a habit of pulling paper out of the recycling, sure, you can, with enough effort, teach your dog not to do that. In the meantime, you can also get a recycling bin with a lid. To that end, I’ve been trying three things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Remove all my social media apps from my cellphone. Any social media consumption must been done on larger and less convenient devices. My phone still has a web browser however, so this is only a minor speed bump for accessing the bad internet.</li>
<li>Work on having my cellphone spend less time in my pocket. I’ve gotten an alarm clock and started wearing a watch to support this goal. It’s remarkable how uncomfortable I feel when my phone isn’t in my pocket.</li>
<li>Limit my social media and internet browsing to 30 minutes per day. Picking an amount of time was interesting. 30 minutes felt impossible short. But committing to spending an hour or more on social media per day felt obviously much too long. This felt complicated because I have friends I made on the internet who I only interact with on social media.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is all still a work in progress, but I feel like I’m finally finding some strategies that are working a little better than “if you’re not enjoying browsing the internet, just stop and do something else”, because once I’m in the ludic loop, it’s very hard to break out of it. If you were to pick an amount of time to spend on social media and web browsing each day, what amount of time would you pick?</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>You Should Read The Broken Earth Trilogy</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-11-22-you-should-read-the-broken-earth-trilogy.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-11-22-you-should-read-the-broken-earth-trilogy.html</id>
    <published>2020-11-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-11-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on November 22, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>“Let’s start with the end of the world, why don’t we? Get it over with and move on to more interesting things.”</p>
<p>BANG! POW! Dang. That’s how you start a novel. My goodness. MMM.</p>
<p><em>The Broken Earth Trilogy</em> (<em>The Fifth Season</em>, <em>The Obelisk Gate</em>, <em>The Stone Sky</em>) by N.K. Jemisin is rich, dark, brutal and hopeful. You should read it right now.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>It’s tempting to say Jemisin takes the tropes and structures of science fiction and fantasy and subverts them, but I think that isn’t quite the right way of saying it. Not quite the right atmosphere. It felt more like Jemisin took the tropes of sci-fi/fantasy that I’ve grown up with and filled them to bursting with a nuance, depth and immediacy I had barely realized I was missing.</p>
<p>Of course, I grew up reading stories about people who looked like me. Expressed their gender like me. I grew up with fantasy heroes from worlds built on the foundation of an idealized, glossy, magical version of medieval Europe that mirrored the glossy version of history I was taught in grade school. If you grew up reading sci-fi/fantasy and the heroes weren’t so clearly modelled on your identity and your history, all those things I barely realized were missing were probably glaringly, painfully obvious to you.</p>
<p><em>Broken Earth</em> tackles what feels like the two most pressing issues facing the world today: racism and environmental catastrophe. And Jemisin does it brilliantly. Jemisin is the first person to win the Hugo award three years in a row and the first person to win it for all three books in a trilogy. Despite all these accolades, I picked up <em>The Fifth Season</em> in Powell’s and put it down what must have been a dozen times. I think I was a little intimidated by how serious it sounded, and I would walk out the door with something lighter. I’m so glad to have finally read it. Jemisin asks what it means to be human, what it means to be a part of a community, what it means to love, and what it means to attempt the impossible. I’ll be thinking about it for a long time.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>When Did I Stop Reading?</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-10-14-when-did-i-stop-reading.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-10-14-when-did-i-stop-reading.html</id>
    <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on October 14, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Today’s mood: “Crazy Over You” - BLACKPINK</p>
<p>Somehow, sometime, I think I stopped reading novels. Not completely, but mostly. When I was a kid, reading was pretty much all I did.</p>
<p>After singing its praises for what felt like months, Kate finally broke through and I picked up <em>Gideon the Ninth</em> by Tamsyn Muir. I read it straight through and didn’t get to bed until 4AM. Which definitely hits a bit harder than it used to. Demonstrating an absolutely astounding amount of self-control I spaced the sequal, <em>Harrow the Ninth</em>, out over two days. It was a delight. <em>Gideon</em> is achingly romantic, exquisitely crafted, and set in a world somewhere between Gormenghast and Warhammer 40,000. Obviously I loved it.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>My complete disinterest in pacing myself when it comes to fantasy has stopped me from reading, and that’s a real shame. I have even tried reading boring books (Sorry, Tolkein, but the first place I turned was <em>The Silmarillion</em>) so that I wouldn’t stay up all night. Which basically worked… but then I got bored, didn’t finish it, and didn’t pick up another book for quite a while. <em>Titus Groan</em> by Mervyn Peak hit a perfect mark of slow enough that I didn’t stay up <em>all</em> night, but engrossing enough that I made it to the end. But searching for books that were boring but not too boring wasn’t something that I could really get excited about. And I didn’t read much.</p>
<p>I love reading.</p>
<p>I love it so much.</p>
<p><em>Gideon</em> reminded me of that. It’s time to accept that I prefer to read to excess. To overwhelm myself. To stuff myself.</p>
<p>To novels! And to staying up past your bedtime reading them!</p>
<p>Also, trying out this blog thing again :)</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Thinking About Stages - Part 1</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-05-04-thinking-about-stages-part-1.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-05-04-thinking-about-stages-part-1.html</id>
    <published>2020-05-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-05-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May  4, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Today’s mood: “Fetch the Bolt Cutters” - Fiona Apple</p>
<p>Kate asked me to give a short presentation to her architecture firm to start a discussion about stages. I figured it was a good push to begin to reengage with my performance practice, and a chance to dust off the old blog! I’ll be posting little thought snippets that will eventually serve as notes/outlines for the presentation.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="thought-1-eye-contact-prosceniums-and-arenas.">Thought 1: Eye Contact, Prosceniums, and Arenas.</h2>
<p>First off, two quick diagrams, with “P” for performer and “A” for audience to define the basic proscenium and arena arrangements. Both stage types can range from huge concert halls and sports arenas to small and intimate spaces with only a handful of audience members.</p>
<h3 id="proscenium">Proscenium</h3>
<pre><code>  PP
------
AAAAAA
AAAAAA</code></pre>
<h3 id="arena">Arena</h3>
<pre><code>AAAAAAAAAA
AA+----+AA
AA|    |AA
AA| PP |AA
AA|    |AA
AA+----+AA
AAAAAAAAAA</code></pre>
<h3 id="basic-relationships">Basic Relationships</h3>
<p><strong>Performer-Audience Relationship:</strong> In the proscenium, the performers can face the entire audience, while in the arena the performer can only face a small portion of the audience at any given time.</p>
<p><strong>Performer-Performer Relationship:</strong> A common technique for two performers having a conversation on a proscenium stage is to “cheat out”, meaning artificially rotate themselves towards the audience while talking to give the audience more of a three-quarters view of their bodies, rather than a side profile. In the arena, because there are always audience members at every angle, the idea of cheating out doesn’t function the same way, and performers can face each other directly without feeling like they are turning away from the audience.</p>
<p><strong>Audience-Audience Relationship:</strong> In a proscenium, the relationship between audience members is typically supressed, both by the lighting, and by the fact that you can only see the backs of other audience members heads, which are generally less interesting than their faces. In an arena, being able to see across the stage to the audience members who are facing you creates an opportunity for significantly more audience-audience visual engagement. Depending on the reason a performance has been staged in an arena arrangment, this audience-audience relationship may be highlighted or supressed. Sports events are a type of performance where the audience-audience relationship is particularly important, typically with the audience both lit and organized to amplify the rivalry between fans of the two teams.</p>
<h3 id="more-to-come">More to Come!</h3>
<p>That’s all for today! I just wanted to get down some basic building blocks before trying to tackle what these building blocks might mean for performers and audiences. This is all pretty basic stuff, but I’m shaking off the dust and clearing the cobwebs out of my brain, so starting simple feels good.</p>
<p>More to come soon on this meandering tour through my thoughts on the relationships, scales, and formalities of different stages, and how those characteristics become a part of the performances on those stages!</p>
<p>I’m also planning on getting digital platforms such as Twitch-style streaming and Zoom-style video-calls into this exploration of the different “shapes” of stages. So more to come on that too!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>100 Day Project</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-04-04-100-day-project.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-04-04-100-day-project.html</id>
    <published>2020-04-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on April  4, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Today’s mood: “Wuthering Heights” - Kate Bush</p>
<p>A quick note to make a commitment.</p>
<p>I’m going to do <a href="https://www.the100dayproject.org/">the 100 day project</a> from April 7 to July 15. According to their website, the project originated <a href="https://designobserver.com/feature/five-years-of-100-days/24678">in this design workshop</a>.</p>
<p>The only thing left to do is commit to a specific action to perform every day. Contenders include: draw a goblin (draw 100 goblins) and, more open-endedly, fill a page with drawings (fill 100 pages with drawings).</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Architecture and Imagery</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-01-25-architecture-and-imagery.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-01-25-architecture-and-imagery.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on January 25, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Today’s mood: “I Want to Grow Up” - Colleen Green</strong></p>
<p>Sometimes I imagine what I would teach if I were given free rein to design an architecture studio. This is by far the best one I’ve come up with.</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="arch-505-architecture-and-imagery">ARCH 505: Architecture and Imagery</h3>
<p><em>In this design studio, the sole means of architectural representation will be the spoken word. The goal is to strengthen the imagination and to harness the descriptive power and flexibility of language. We will explore literary imagery, acting theory, imagination games, memory techniques, meditation and more. The final presentation of the design work will be a monologue.</em></p>
<hr />
<h3 id="inspiration">Inspiration</h3>
<p>In fantasy novels, when the hero must learn to strengthen their mind in order to do magic, it’s totally badass. It gets me going. I love it. See channeling in <em>The Wheel of Time</em> or alar in <em>The Name of the Wind</em>. Only when their minds are strong enough can they speak the words to do magic.</p>
<p>This is also how stories work. A storyteller with a strong mind can speak the words to transport you to another world.</p>
<p>As an architect, could I develop the ability to do this too?</p>
<p>I hope so.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Back to Art/School</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-01-11-art-class.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-01-11-art-class.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on January 11, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Today’s mood: <em>Blood</em> - Kelsey Lu</p>
<p>I’ve been trying to figure out how to rekindle the things I loved back when I was making art in Vancouver. Sometimes I reread this review of <a href="https://www.straight.com/arts/vancouver-fringe-festival-review-mr-boat-heads-electrical-dream-ship-makes-you-think-about-narrative-conventions">Mr. Boat-head’s Electrical Dreamship</a> by Colin Thomas and get real nostalgic. This probably isn’t a terrible healthy activity. My glasses are probably a little rose-tinted. (Also, actual rose-tinted glasses are great. I should get some.)</p>
<p>Perhaps getting back to the past isn’t so complicated as I’d imagined. Kate bought me an art class at <a href="https://www.radiusstudio.org/">Radius</a> with <a href="https://www.lettiejane.com/">Lettie Jane Rennekamp</a>. The first class was last Wednesday and it felt real good. And all I have to do is show up!</p>
<p>We did blind contour drawings of clothes, plants, each other. We painted over them with watercolors. We looked at each others work and talked about it. We did it several times. It was quiet, but it felt like a return. A return to exactly what, I’m not sure. But I felt engaged in a way that I haven’t felt in a long time.</p>
<p>Sometimes it’s hard to get started. Taking a class seems like a pretty good start. I’m looking forward to seeing where this goes.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Shouting into the Void Again</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-01-05-shouting-into-the-void-again.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2020-01-05-shouting-into-the-void-again.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on January  5, 2020
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Today’s mood: <a href="https://hachep.bandcamp.com/track/somnambulate">Somnabulate by H.P. Parmley</a>.</p>
<p>Sometimes we have to try things more than once. In honor of the new decade, or just because I went on a losing streak in the MTGO Vintage Cube and need to take a break, I am reviving this old-school-blog-thing. <a href="https://www.brendanalbano.com2020-01-05-shouting-into-the-void-again.html">More details about it in the first post.</a> Just like last time, I’m not sure where it’s going, but social media hasn’t been feeling real great lately, so I’m gonna explore this piece of anti-social media. Not gonna beat myself up about not getting very far with it last time, just gonna use it when it feels like a serves a purpose, and right now, it’s feeling purposeful.</p>
<p>Love,</p>
<p>Brendan</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Fitness Plan and Knee Health</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-08-29-fitness-plan-and-knee-health.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-08-29-fitness-plan-and-knee-health.html</id>
    <published>2018-08-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on August 29, 2018
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>In my previous post I mentioned I was embarking on a new fitness plan, so here’s the deets. The goal is to stop injuring myself whenever I start getting into hiking or running, which has happened a number of times over a number of years now. Most recently, my knee started hurting on my recent trip to Goat Rocks.</p>
<p>I’ve been mentally rehashing all the research I’ve done each time I’ve hurt myself, be it foot, ankle, or knee pain. And like a conspiracy theorist pinning red string between newspaper clippings, I’ve come to the conclusion that weak glutes are definitely a problem for me.</p>
<ul>
<li>Weak glutes are often listed as a potential cause of many of the ailments I’ve had.</li>
<li>When I got a running coach/PT to assess my running form, the main form cue they recommended for me based on what they saw was to squeeze my glutes each step.</li>
<li>I sit at a computer all day at work. A surefire recipe for weak glutes.</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to the glutes, I know I need to work on ankle mobility, ankle strength, and dynamic balance.</p>
<p>Last summer I was dealing with plantar fasciitis, and I tackled it with a combination of minimal shoes, toe spacers, and some exercises from <a href="https://www.nwfootankle.com/">NW Foot and Ankle</a>. It’s taken over a year, which I’ve read can be common with PF, and while I don’t think I’m 100% better, the Goat Rocks trip I experienced zero PF pain, so that was really exciting!</p>
<p>This summer I knew I needed to up my mobility and balance and Kate and I started doing Yoga with Adriene on YouTube every day, and it’s been pretty great. Up until the knee pain on the Goat Rocks trip, my knees have been better than they ever have before, and I had actually been enjoying hiking downhill for the first time this summer. But while the daily yoga practice seems to be helping, it looks like I need even more help!</p>
<p>So I’ve concocted a plan. It’s going to be a lot of work, so I’m posting about it for a bit of accountability, and also to remind myself where I started and why I’m doing this when I think about quitting.</p>
<p>I want my hiking to be limited by my cardio. I want to hike until I’m tired. I’m sick of hiking until I get hurt. Time to change that!</p>
<h1 id="in-the-morning-simple-and-sinister">In the morning: Simple and Sinister</h1>
<p>I’ve found that I have a better track record with short workouts I can do every day, rather than long workouts a few times a week. I also seem to do a little better with at-home workouts. “Simple and Sinister” is a workout program by Pavel Tsatsouline focussing on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yHxcTn1UeAc">kettlebell swing</a> and the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0bWRPC49-KI">Turkish get-up</a>. It takes about 25-40 minutes and you do it more or less every day, with occasional rest days as you need them or as life gets in the way.</p>
<h1 id="throughout-the-day-glute-kegels">Throughout the day: Glute Kegels</h1>
<p>I encountered these in a <a href="https://medium.com/@OVCM/how-i-fixed-my-knee-injury-in-time-to-hike-2-450-miles-this-summer-61fe599205e3">blog post about a hiker fixing their knee up before a successful PCT thruhike</a> and they sound great. Basically, throughout the day, you squeeze your butt. That’s it!</p>
<h1 id="in-the-evening-yoga-with-adrienne">In the evening: Yoga with Adrienne</h1>
<p>Kate and I have been doing Yoga with Adrienne on youtube and it’s been really great. Her instruction style seems to be just right for us at the moment, and we’ve managed to stick to it for several months now, so in an effort to not fix what ain’t broke, I’m still on the Yoga with Adrienne every day train!</p>
<h1 id="goals">Goals</h1>
<p>Goals are important! While my primary goal is pain free hiking, that’s hard to measure, so my first goal is to hit 10x10 (10 sets of 10 reps) kettlebell swings with 24kg, 10x1 (10 sets of 1 rep) turkish get-ups with 16kg, and be able to recover fully each day. Right now I’m on 5 sets of each, and am pretty burnt after two or three days.</p>
<p>I’ve been doing this plan for a little over a week now, and my consistency hasn’t been perfect, but it’s hasn’t been too bad, and it makes me feel good (physically and emotionally) every time I complete a workout, so that’s encouraging! Just gotta stick to it for like 6 months now ;)</p>
<p>And lastly, if you’d like to see me shirtless, [here’s a “before pic” and a cunningly photoshopped “after” pic showing my goals of improved posture and a rockin’ booty]({{ “/assets/2018-08-29-fitness-plan/goals.gif” | absolute_url }}).</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Ultralight Backpacking Introduction</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-08-23-ultralight-backpacking-intro.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-08-23-ultralight-backpacking-intro.html</id>
    <published>2018-08-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-08-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on August 23, 2018
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>One of the main topics of this blog is ultralight backpacking, so I thought I’d take a stab at writing up a quick intro to the concept. I’d say I’m at most an advanced beginner when it comes to backpacking, so well, you know, this is all, just, like, my opinion, man.</p>
<p>Ok caveats and disclaimers out of the way. Here goes:</p>
<h1 id="the-big-idea">The big idea</h1>
<p>The goal of ultralight backpacking is to hike more comfortably and more efficiently by bringing less gear, bringing lighter gear, and taking advantage of multi-use gear.</p>
<p>Typically “Ultralight” is defined as a base pack weight (BPW) of less than 10 lbs, where BPW is the weight of all the gear in your pack, not including food, water and fuel. The weight including food water and fuel is total pack weight (TPW), and is also a useful number. Like everything, the 10 lb benchmark is a tool to help you enjoy your time in the outdoors more. You can use it however serves you best.</p>
<h1 id="how-to-get-started">How to get started</h1>
<p>If you’re keen on going ultralight, the most critical step to lightening your pack is to get a scale. You want something that is good for weighing things in the 0-5 lb range. A kitchen scale is great. A bathroom scale is not super helpful. Trying to guess how much things weigh by hefting them in one hand and saying “Hmmmmm” totally doesn’t work.</p>
<p>The first pass at lightening your pack can typically be accomplished by releasing your preconceived notions of what you need to bring to go backpacking, doing a bunch of research, and thinking critically and carefully about the gear you choose to take with you.</p>
<p>After that, the pursuit of traveling more efficiently and more comfortably usually requires making trade offs of various sorts. This is a moment where your preconceived notions can really get in your way. Step back and consider the trade offs with a bit of emotional distance. You want to make the tradeoffs such that the thing you are getting adds more to your experience than the thing you are giving up. Don’t be afraid to give things up!</p>
<p>The gear that you bring should always be adequate to keep you safe and should be designed to increase the joy that backpacking brings you. Both of these factors are highly personal and subjective, and that’s where the fun of thinking about your gear really begins!</p>
<p>I’ve found that lightening my pack over a series of low-risk overnight trips is a very effective way to experiment and figure out what works for me and what doesn’t.</p>
<h1 id="resources">Resources</h1>
<p>On the bunch of research note, here are some books and websites that I go to for research:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Ultralight/">r/ultralight</a></li>
<li>Mike Clelland’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Ultralight-Backpackin-Tips-Inexpensive-Lightweight/dp/0762763841">“Ultralight Backpackin’ Tips”</a></li>
<li>Ray Jardine’s <a href="http://www.rayjardine.com/ray-way/Books/Trail-Life/index.htm">“Trail Life”</a></li>
<li>Liz Thomas’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Backpacker-Long-Trails-Mastering-Thru-Hike/dp/1493028723">“Long Trails”</a></li>
<li><a href="https://andrewskurka.com/tag/core-13/">Andrew Skurka’s Core 13 clothing articles</a></li>
</ul>
<p>And here are some places to find used gear:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ulgeartrade">r/ulgeartrade</a></li>
<li><a href="https://backpackinglight.com/forums/forum/commerce/gear-swap/">Backpacking Light Gear Swap Forum</a></li>
</ul>
<p>And when overwhelmed by the options for ultralight backpacking gear, you can never go too far wrong with <a href="https://mountainlaureldesigns.com/">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> for new gear and the <a href="http://www.rayjardine.com/ray-way/OrderForm.php">Ray-way kits</a> for getting started with MYOG if you want a little more guidance than just buying some raw materials and having a go at it (maybe pass on the blood cleaner kit and focus on the backpacking stuff though).</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Goat Rocks, Packwood, Mt. Adams Trip Report</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-08-18-goat-rocks-packwood-mt-adams-trip-report.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-08-18-goat-rocks-packwood-mt-adams-trip-report.html</id>
    <published>2018-08-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-08-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on August 18, 2018
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <figure>
<img src="https://www.brendanalbano.com/images/2018-08-18-goat-rocks/tarp-at-goat-lake.JPG" alt="Tarp at Goat Lake" />
<figcaption aria-hidden="true">Tarp at Goat Lake</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>First trip report on the new blog! In which Kate and I go on a backpacking trip with a bunch of strangers from the internet and live to tell the tale! (edit: and in which I stream of consciousness write a whole lot of words and don’t edit them. You have been warned!)</p>
<p>I forget how it all started, but at some point, I was chatting online (seems thematic for this old-school blog idea) with a bunch of folks from the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ultralight">ultralight subreddit</a> and someone said we should all go on a trip together. And then all of a sudden folks were taking time off work and getting flights and coming up with trip ideas. Since a good chunk of us were located in the PNW, a 5 day trip through the Goat Rocks solidified as our plan… until a few days before we were supposed to leave the Miriam Fire started and everything went a little haywire.</p>
<p>Complicating matters was that Scott and Sam were planning to do a route doing a 360 around Mt. Adams that Scott had devised immediately before the 5 day Goat Rocks trip, and they wouldn’t have cell service. But due to the uncertainties about smoke from the Miriam Fire, we were planning to call the ranger station and ask about the conditions the day before we left. If conditions looked okay, we’d go ahead with the Goat Rocks trip, and if not, we’d frantically developed a backup plan in the Alpine Lakes Wilderness.</p>
<p>To solve the communication problem, it was decided that Monday morning (the day before our Tuesday-Saturday trip) Kate and I would call the ranger station, get whatever info we could, make a decision with the rest of the crew still in cellphone range, then drive to Walupt Lake, where we would meet up with Scott and Sam and let them know which trip we were doing, and if necessary, shuttle them back to their car so we could all drive to Alpine Lakes.</p>
<h1 id="day-0-driving-to-walupt-lake">Day 0: Driving to Walupt Lake</h1>
<p><em>Portland -&gt; Trout Lake -&gt; Walupt Lake</em></p>
<p>We called the ranger station first thing on Monday and the ranger said that they hadn’t gotten any reports about the Miriam Fire smoke yet, but thought the wind would be in our favor and didn’t try to dissuade us from our planned itinerary. They also told us that a washout on Coyote Trail 79 that we were worried about had just been repaired. We decided to go ahead with our Goat Rocks trip with the knowledge that we might have to adapt our itinerary if the smoke ended up being bad. I also was a little suspicious that I wasn’t in good enough shape to handle our planned itinerary, but I figured, like the fire, I’d just have to adapt when the issue came up!</p>
<p>We had taken the bus down to Eugene the previous day to borrow my parents’ car and driven it back to Portland, so after we confirmed our itinerary with the rest of the crew, we headed out to find Scott and Sam at Walupt Lake.</p>
<p>We had all day to make our way there, so we took the scenic route via Highway 14 on the north side of the gorge and then headed north through Trout Lake.</p>
<p>When we stopped at the burger joint/coffee shop/gas station in Trout Lake, the place was swarming with PCT thruhikers, and I quickly spotted someone I followed on instagram which was a trip! After finishing our burgers, I asked the folks I recognized from instagram if they needed a ride and they did! And a short one at that! And it turns out the place Kate and I are moving in September isn’t too far from where some of them live in Portland! Making new friends already!</p>
<p>This was the first of many firsts on this trip for me, and I was quite tickled to give a ride to a crew of PCT hikers. Our trip is done now, but they’re still hiking and you can follow along at <a href="http://www.soletosoil.com">Homework’s blog</a>. My cameo is in the day 5 entry posted August 7th. I’m basically famous now as far as I can tell.</p>
<p>The rest of the drive was pretty low-key, and we found Sam and Scott sprawled out on the side of the road about a mile from Walupt Lake and gave them a ride the rest of the way. We got a car camping spot at the lake and set up our shelters and fed them snacks and beer as they recovered from their Adams 360 adventure.</p>
<h1 id="day-1-big-climb-to-goat-lake">Day 1: Big climb to Goat Lake</h1>
<p><em>Walupt Lake -&gt; Nanny Ridge Trail 98 -&gt; PCT -&gt; Snowgrass Trail 96 -&gt; Goat Lake</em></p>
<p>On Tuesday morning, the rest of our crew started rolling in, and soon the 9 of us were gathered at the trailhead ready to tackle a big climb up Nannie Ridge Trail 98. 1900 ft of elevation gain over 2.4 miles got us all sweating right off the bat. The heat didn’t help either. Eventually we joined up with the PCT and started seeing a fair number of other hikers.</p>
<p>We all got a chuckle when a group of thruhikers said we were the most ultralight sectionhikers ever, and Sam demoed his footcare system to a hiker who was having trouble with their blisters, complete with taking off his shoes and getting out the leukotape.</p>
<p>Shortly after Cispus Pass, and as we were all just about to melt from the heat, we came across a small streamcrossing with a waterfall! Our group had gotten pretty stretched out at this point, as we were all hiking different speeds, but we collected up at the waterfall, where the cold mist made the area significantly more pleasant. We lingered as long as we could, but eventually it was time to move on, heading towards the cutoff that would take us off the PCT and onto Snowgrass Trail 96 towards Goat Lake.</p>
<p>Most of Tuesday was spent walking through charming alpine meadows, with small patches of conniferous trees and views of high peaks in every direction. It was gorgeous.</p>
<p>During the last mile or so of the hike, my knee started to hurt on the downhills. This was immediately worrying and frustrating! I’d done an overnight a few weeks back with similar mileage and elevation to this first day and my knees had felt amazing. But now my right knee was hurting. I tried not to stress too much about what it meant for the rest of the trip, and slowly picked my way down, then back up to Goat Lake where we were planning on camping.</p>
<p>Goat Lake was gorgeous, surrounded by mountains and with a few icebergs hanging on late into the summer. The wind coming off the lake was cold, and Scott set up his shelter on the shore while the rest of us headed back down a few hundred feet to set up where it was slightly warmer.</p>
<p>After making our pesto pasta salad (cold soaked ramen with pesto sauce) for dinner, we crawled under our tarp and wrapped up in our quilts and, aside from the knee, I was feeling great.</p>
<h1 id="day-2-the-adventure-begins">Day 2: The adventure begins</h1>
<p><em>Goat Lake -&gt; Snowgrass Trail 96 -&gt; PCT -&gt; Coyote Trail 79 -&gt; Upper Lake Trail 81 -&gt; Packwood Lake</em></p>
<p>Either in the morning, or the previous evening, we decided that rather than take our planned loop down Goat Ridge Trail 95 then back up Snowgrass, we would just head straight back to the PCT and onwards towards the knife edge and perhaps end up camping at Lost Lake. This would cut some miles off both today’s and tomorrow’s itineraries, which was fine by me, since my knee hadn’t magically fixed itself overnight.</p>
<p>We started off and Kate and I quickly fell towards the back of the group as I was walking slow and taking a lot of breaks. I found that if I hiked slow for an hour, then took a 20 min break to rest my knee and stretch my legs, I felt like I could keep on hiking without things getting worse. We played leapfrog with Chris, whose feet were hurting and was also taking it easy. Kate gave me her trekking pole, so I could hike with two poles for most of the day (we had each been using one pole up until this point).</p>
<p>Day 2 was full of big alpine views, which was pretty dang cool! And the big alpine views was what several of our friends who had flown across the country were most excited about for this hike!</p>
<p>Either just before, or at the beginning of the knife edge (I’m not sure where it officially starts) there were a few snow crossing. Most of them were fairly low-key, although you definitely had to pay attention, and I gave Kate her trekking pole back so we each had a pole for the snow. But the middle one felt pretty scary. I don’t have a lot of experience evaluating snow crossings, but this one was pretty clearly of the if you fell it would be real bad variety, and while there were footsteps to walk in, they didn’t feel super secure. I’d been walking in front because I was slower, with Kate behind me, and that turned out to be good on this section because about halfway through the scary crossing Kate said her adrenaline was really starting to pump and she could feel the impulse to go faster which she knew of course was not a good idea, so I continued to walk slow, and we kept up a conversation about nothing, trying to strike a balance of still focussing intently on our foot placements, but also offering something else to focus on to take the edge off the adrenaline.</p>
<p>We made it through the snow without incident, and tried not to dwell too much on the fact that our planned itinerary had us doing these crossing again at the end of the trip. After the snow came the knife edge, which was gorgeous. Kate was a little distracted by the aftereffects of the adrenaline, and I was a little distracted by worrying about my knee, but the views on the knife edge were breathtaking.</p>
<p>After the knife edge, we were hiking with Matt, and as he hiked up a small rise in front of us, he turned around and shouted back, “You’re not gonna like this.”</p>
<p>As we crested the rise we saw a lot of smoke far of in the distance from the Miriam fire. But then we saw what he was pointing at, a brand new plume of smoke in the valley that our itinerary had us passing through the following day. We had already been a little bit hesitant of our plan to hike back on the Clear Fork trail, just becuase of the smoke, but this sealed the deal. We were going to have to reroute.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Chris was somewhere behind us, Spencer, Sean, Sarah and Sam were all up ahead of us, and we were fairly sure that Scott was behind us, but hadn’t talked to him since the morning when he was heading off to explore Hawkeye Point and planning to catch up with us later.</p>
<p>We pulled out our maps and phones and concluded that the smart thing to do would be for everyone to keep hiking on our planned route for a few more miles, then gather at Packwood Saddle, where we had an option of hiking out down to Packwood Lake, or perhaps camping in that general vicinity, and doing an out-and-back of the trails we had already hiked. We just hoped the rest of our friends had come to the same conclusion!</p>
<p>Thankfully, they had, and when we finally made our way to Packwood Saddle, everyone was waiting, tired, thirsty, and being swarmed by flies. The flies didn’t seem to be the biting kind at least, so that was a bonus!</p>
<p>After a fair amount of discussion, it was concluded that most folks were more interested in hiking down to Packwood Lake and either figuring out how to string together a bunch of winding forest roads and connect back up with the Lily Basin Trail. We’d camp at the beginning of the Lily Basin Trail, then hike back to Goat Lake the following day. Or alternatively, we could hitch into the town of Packwood, then from there hitch back to our cars at Walupt Lake.</p>
<p>After we’d decided we were commited to camping down at Packwood Lake, the folks who were suffering the most from the flies headed down towards the lake, and the rest of us waited for Scott and Chris to pass on the decision.</p>
<p>During all of the waiting and flies and sitting around at Packwood Saddle, Sam had deployed the pro move of rolling out his CCF pad and taking a nap with his backpack as a pillow. That was definitely a pro move!</p>
<p>Eventually Scott and Chris showed up, and the plan was communicated, and Kate and I headed down towards the lake while Scott and Sam made dinner in Packwood Saddle.</p>
<p>Kate and I played leapfrog with Chris for a while, and eventually Scott and Sam zipped by us. We rolled into camp a little after sunset, and thankfully were able to hear voices and spot the flimmer of headlamps reflecting off of Cuben Fiber in the dark to find our friends. Chris rolled in a little later and we all saw his headlamp and shouted to make sure he didn’t miss us.</p>
<p>After a long and exhausting day, especially with the added stress of nursing my injured knee along, we were rewarded with a warm and miraculously bug free night. Kate and I decided to skip setting up our tarp and cowboy camp, which was great fun, and was something we’d never done before. Falling asleep on our sheet of polycryo, staring up at the stars and tree branches was delightful.</p>
<h1 id="day-3-hitchin-wheelin-and-car-campin">Day 3: Hitchin’, wheelin’, and car campin’</h1>
<p><em>Packwood Lake Trail 78 -&gt; Packwood -&gt; Walupt Lake -&gt; Packwood -&gt; Car camping off the side of the road</em></p>
<p>The following morning, we hiked out towards the Packwood Lake trailhead, which was about 6 miles away. Initially, Matt and Chris were planning on hitching into Packwood and taking it easy and eventually hitching their way back to Walupt to meet us at our cars Saturday, while the rest of us would hike the forest roads to connect to the Lily Basin Trail.</p>
<p>My knee continued to hurt, but thankfully wasn’t getting any worse as we hiked this morning. It did mean I was hiking a lot closer to 1 MPH than my usual 2 MPH however.</p>
<p>When those of us who were planning to head to Lily Basin all collected at the trailhead, we sat down and tried as best we could to count up the mileage of forest roads to make the connection. Initially we had hoped to be able to make a shortcut and bushwack from one road to another at one point, but a closer look at the topography ruled out that idea.</p>
<p>Because of how the roads twisted and turned, it ended up looking like around 12 miles of forest road walking to get to where we would be camping at the beginning of the Lily Basin Trail.</p>
<p>At 2 MPH, we could get there by nightful, but I knew I couldn’t keep up that pace for 12 miles, and I told the group that at the pace I’d been hiking, it would probably take me until midnight to make it to our destination, so that was basically a no-go for me, and I’d have to hitch into Packwood. Everyone was very understanding, and decided to hitch to Packwood as well rather than split up further. And no one had been particularly excited about spending the whole day walking winding dirt roads in the forest.</p>
<p>While we had been hemming and hawing about our plans, we turned down a hitch with a big church group, and of course we decided that we did indeed want a hitch immediately after they pulled out of the parking lot. Serendipitously, Matt and Chris emerged from the trail behind us and we were all reunited, now that we were all heading to Packwood. We eventually all managed to hitch into Packwood in a series of small groups, and while there was no cell service in Packwood, we all collected up at Cruiser’s pizza, as that seemed to be the obvious gathering place. We had burgers and pizza and beer and chitchatted with the PCT hikers who were refueling and charging their batteries while we planned our next moves.</p>
<p>After a few failed attempts at the coffee shop and gas station looking for a ride, Kate managed to score a ride back to Walupt Lake from the owner of the ski shop next door. It was incredibly generous of him, considering he closed his shop early to drive us an hour back to our cars! Kate, Spencer and I went with him, so that we could then drive two cars back to Packwood to pick up the 9 of us, and then drive us all back up to Walupt. There was a lot of driving ahead of us, but it felt great to have some plans nailed down finally.</p>
<p>This was my first time hitching a ride, and I started using the list of firsts for me on this trip as a great way to keep my spirits up while struggling with my knee.</p>
<p>Walupt Lake campground was totally full, so as we drove back, we kept our eyes out for dispersed campsites on the side of the road where we could car camp before heading out again to do one more night of backpacking.</p>
<p>When we got into town, everyone hit the grocery store, and we tried to buy fun food for car camping. Car camping is a skill that most of us don’t have all that well developped, but we did our best, with a lot of chips, guacamole, and beer being purchased.</p>
<p>Then we headed back up the road to Walupt Lake for the 3rd time that day, and began to search for a campsite. There were a few scares about our creeky old cars overheating, and a bit of smoke that was concluded to just be my parents’ car that we had borrowed burning a little oil.</p>
<p>We explored a few side roads looking for campsites and Scott and Sam gave me instructions about how to not high-center the car, and how to drive over large rocks, which was another first. Presumably, this didn’t count as off-roading, becuase, for one, we were on a road, but for a city-dweller like me, it felt pretty dang adventurous! Unfortunately, the adventurous routes to campsites were all a bust, and we had to back track, and eventually made our way to a pretty nice spot just off the road that we had spied on our way down. There was a big open area where we could park the cars, watch the stars, etc., and tucked away behind us was a stream, and some softer ground for setting up shelters.</p>
<p>We learned that in addition to my knee being hurt, and Chris’s feet being one giant hotspot, Chris had had been a bit sick in Packwood, Sarah had gotten stung by a bee while waiting for us to return with the cars, so a low mileage day and a night of carcamping seemed like it was just the thing many of us needed.</p>
<p>Despite the comedy of a group of ultralight backpackers trying to car camp, we all had a great time hanging out and eating chips before rolling up into our little hiker burritos and cowboy camping and watching the stars.</p>
<h1 id="day-4-mt.-adams-high-camp">Day 4: Mt. Adams High Camp</h1>
<p><em>Walupt Lake -&gt; Killen Creek Trailhead -&gt; High Camp</em></p>
<p>In the morning we decided that we’d head to Walupt Lake to collect Chris’s car, and he’d probably head out, since his feet were beat up, then we’d all make our way towards the Muddy Meadows trailhead where Scott’s car was, and from there head to the Killen Creek Trailhead on Mt Adams and hike up to High Camp.</p>
<p>Sam decided to head back into Portland since he’d already done this hike at the beginning of the week and he needed a little time to get his stuff organized before flying home.</p>
<p>Scott graciously played tour guide for us as we hiked up to high camp. We’d done this same hike with Scott a few weeks earlier when he was scoping out different parts of the Mt Adams route, so we took it slow and the rest of the group raced ahead.</p>
<p>The hike from Killen Creek to High Camp is relatively short, but the views are incredible. The views/effort ratio is really off the charts, and I highly recommend it as an overnight trip for anyone in Portland or nearby.</p>
<p>When we’d done the trip with Scott, we’d camped SE of high camp in a cool flat area, and we met the crew up there, but it was concluded that it was a little too windy and there weren’t quite enough spots for all our shelters. My knee didn’t feel quite up for the side trip to Lake 7505, so I had to pass on that, but we’d gone up there on our trip a few weeks back and it was gorgeous. I definitely recommend making your way up to the lake if you do this trip! Sarah also joined Kate and I in heading back down to high camp rather than heading up to the lake since she was suffering from a combination of a headcold and the bee sting on her ankle was pretty swolen and uncomfortable.</p>
<p>After much hemming and hawing about where to find wind breaks to set up our shelters, we eventually set up at high camp and relaxed. The Perseids meteor shower was getting going this evening and we saw some great shooting stars.</p>
<h1 id="day-5-heading-home">Day 5: Heading home</h1>
<p><em>High Camp -&gt; Killen Creek Trailhead -&gt; Trout Lake -&gt; Portland</em></p>
<p>Heading home was largely uneventful, but still a nice hike, and my knee continued to maintain the status quo, which was reassuring. We feasted in Trout Lake, and eventually made our way back to Portland.</p>
<p>Between my knee starting to hurt on the first day, reroutes due to fires, having to hitch to Packwood, then to Walupt, struggling with finding a campsite, and generally communicating and balancing the needs and desires of 9 different hikers, there were a lot of challenges on this trip. But it was also absolutely amazing and I had a blast. As Sam said several times, “that’s what makes it an adventure!”</p>
<p>Now that I’m home I’m trying to figure out how to help my knee heal and how to get stronger and be less injury prone. Hurting my knee was hugely frustrating, as we’d gone on a trip recently that we thought had similar mileage and elevation as the rist two days on the Goat Rocks trip, and my knees had felt fabulous. So I’m not entirely sure what the difference was. Perhaps there was more rocky ground in the Goat Rocks that subjected my knee to more forces in unusual directions.</p>
<p>Regardless, my gameplan is to rest my knee and work my butt. A lot of what I’ve read about the knee pain I had seems to indicate that weak glutes are a potential culprit. Weak glutes are also a common affliction of folks who work desk jobs, which I do. So I’m gonna keep up the yoga I’ve been doing, and add in a kettlebell workout, specifically focussing on kettlebell swings to target my glutes, then slowly ease back into hiking.</p>
<p>At the very least, if it doesn’t end up helping with the knee, it should help me develop a great ass, so I figure it’s a win either way.</p>
<p>If you made it all the way through this, thanks for reading my first trip report!</p>
<p>I’ll do another post with some thoughts about gear and that sort of thing.</p>
<p>I’ll also try and add some photos, but just writing this up ended up taking way longer than I expected, so for now, this is it!</p>
<p>Also, for another perspective of the trip, check out Sean’s videos: <a href="https://youtu.be/mh-aXyC5whs">Part 1</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0ZBI7gYld7s&amp;feature=youtu.be">Part 2</a> on youtube! I think <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCo-Gow_76-aVNsoa4BhhIbg">Sam</a> may have a trip videos coming up as well.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Friction and Hobbies</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-07-29-friction-and-hobbies.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-07-29-friction-and-hobbies.html</id>
    <published>2018-07-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on July 29, 2018
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Friction in a retail shopping experience is all the things that get in the way of a customer walking in, picking up the thing they want, and walking out (with the money being automatically deducted from their bank account via brain chip, or whatever). I don’t remember where I came across this concept, and I’m not particularly interested in the nuances of how much friction one (who?) wants in a retail experience, but I did think the idea of friction was pretty cool.</p>
<p>I have a lot of hobbies (this is all going to tie together, just hold on a second).</p>
<p>I have a lot of hobbies that I don’t do very often. I make a piece of ultralight backpacking gear every 3 or 4 months. I carved a handful of spoons a year ago, and haven’t since. I wrote a lot of words during <a href="https://nanowrimo.org">NaNoWriMo</a> one time when I was a teenager. And then again last year. So that’s something like a 15 year gap between my two forrays into writing fiction.</p>
<p>Anyways, the point is, I love doing all these things. They fill me with satisfaction. But the vast majority of the time, the sewing machine is tucked underneath a table. The carving knives are deep in a tool bag. My thoughts about novelling are “maybe next November”. And instead of doing these creative things that bring my a lot of joy, I refresh reddit or scroll through instagram or do any number of mindless, mildly entertaining, but ultimately unsatisfying activities.</p>
<p>I have a lot of trouble starting projects. Also finishing projects.</p>
<p>At some point, I started to notice that instead of trying to just sit down and do the thing, I had better luck if all I did was get set up. Then the following day, with everything already retrieved from the tool bags and layed out nicely, I found it much easier to tackle actually starting the project.</p>
<p>Just getting set up was more likely to feel approachable. And the following day, once I was all set up, getting started was more approachable too. I was reducing friction. And I was learning that I often have a very low capacity to overcome friction to start projects. Such a low capacity that the fairly small amount of friction of unpacking the sewing machine and getting it set up (for example) was enough to stop me from doing any sewing.</p>
<p>So I decided to do an experiment where I picked one hobby (sewing in this case), and cleared off a corner of the desk in my partner and my apartment to have the sewing machine stay set up on for a little while.</p>
<p>I didn’t have a particular project in mind. But I did have a long list of projects that I’d been wanting to get to for months that I hadn’t started. Some of them were tiny, but still, they lingered, undone.</p>
<p>Yesterday I felt motivated to modify our <a href="http://www.rayjardine.com/ray-way/Tarp-Kit/index.htm">Ray-Way Tarp</a> so that our <a href="https://seatosummitusa.com/collections/mobile-outdoor/products/nano-mosquito-pyramid-net-with-insect-shield?variant=7896098963484">S2S Nano Mosquito Pyramid</a> would hang better and wouldn’t require the 1oz spreader bar it comes with. And I waffled. But the sewing machine was already set up. And plugged in. And the bobbin was threaded. And I dove in, and it took maybe 20 minutes at the most and it was done!</p>
<p>Once we test the new setup out I’ll write up a review with lots of pictures.</p>
<p>Until then, I’m pretty pleased with this low-friction sewing project, and the sewing machine is going to continue taking up a sizeable portion of our tiny apartment, and hopefully I’ll be doing a lot more sewing!</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Shouting into the Void</title>
    <link href="https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-07-28-shouting-into-the-void.html" />
    <id>https://www.brendanalbano.com/posts/2018-07-28-shouting-into-the-void.html</id>
    <published>2018-07-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on July 28, 2018
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Hello, world!</p>
<p>I’ve been feeling like social media isn’t making me feel real great lately, and I ran across a <a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2018/03/25/beyond-deletefacebook-more-thoughts-on-embracing-the-social-internet-over-social-media/">blog post by Cal Newport</a> that suggested kicking it old-school and going back to shouting into the void from your own personal website. This really appealed on an emotional level! Getting intellectual about it can be the subject of another post.</p>
<p>Cal Newport references <a href="https://iasc-culture.org/THR/THR_article_2018_Spring_Jacobs.php">a more indepth article</a> about the subject that seems like it will make some good bedtime reading, but I was fired up enough to dive right in and get my blog set up!</p>
<p>Tech-wise, I wanted my blog to require a bit of nerdery, make me feel like a cool computer programmer, and be free. So I’m using <a href="https://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a> to generate the blog, hosting it for free on <a href="https://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a> and writing my posts in <a href="https://www.vim.org">Vim</a>. Locally, this is all running on Ubuntu inside the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/install-win10">Linux Subsystem for Windows</a>.</p>
<p>Anyways, that’s all for now!</p>
<p>Coming soon:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ultralight backpacking trip reports and gear reviews</li>
<li>Pictures of things I’ve made</li>
<li>How I really feel about architecture</li>
</ul>
<p>No comments on this blog, so if you wanna chit chat, feel free to send me an email at brendan@brendanalbano.com</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
